<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A defence of the Appendix. Or A reply to certaine authorities alleaged in answere to a catalogue of Catholike professors, called, An appendix to the Antitdote VVherein also the booke fondly intituled, The Fisher catched in his owne net, is censured. And the sleights of D. Featly, and D. VVhite in shifting off the catalogue of their owne professors, which they vndertooke to shew, are plainly discouered. By L.D. To the Rt. VVorshipfull Syr Humphry Lynde.</title>
            <author>L. D., fl. 1624.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 141 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13235</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23528</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120948</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856139</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856139</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21663</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13235)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21663)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1190:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A defence of the Appendix. Or A reply to certaine authorities alleaged in answere to a catalogue of Catholike professors, called, An appendix to the Antitdote VVherein also the booke fondly intituled, The Fisher catched in his owne net, is censured. And the sleights of D. Featly, and D. VVhite in shifting off the catalogue of their owne professors, which they vndertooke to shew, are plainly discouered. By L.D. To the Rt. VVorshipfull Syr Humphry Lynde.</title>
                  <author>L. D., fl. 1624.</author>
                  <author>Sweet, John, 1570-1632, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at the English College Press] Permissu superiorum,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Saint-Omer :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XXIIII. [1624]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>L.D. = John Sweet? Erroneously attributed to Anthony Champney.</note>
                  <note>A defense of: Norris, Sylvester.  An appendix to the Antidote.</note>
                  <note>"App[arently]. answers a MS. of Lynde's, cf. the book ent[ered]. to R. Milbourne and Eliz. Jaggard 12 ja. 1625"--STC. Also a reply to: Featley, Daniel.  The Fisher catched in his owne net.</note>
                  <note>Identification of printer from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Featley, Daniel, 1582-1645. --  Fisher catched in his owne net --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>S. N. --  (Sylvester Norris), 1572-1630. --  Appendix to the Antidote --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lynde, Humphrey, --  Sir --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Protestantism --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21663:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21663:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Defence of the Appendix. OR A REPLY TO CERTAINE AVTHORITIES alleaged in Anſwere to a Catalogue of Catholike Profeſſors, called, <hi>An Appendix to the Antidote.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVHEREIN Alſo the Booke fondly intituled, <hi>The Fisher catched in his owne Net,</hi> is cenſured. And the ſleights of D. <hi>Featly,</hi> and <hi>D. VVhite</hi> in ſhifting off the Catalogue of their owne Profeſſors, which they vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertooke to ſhew, are plainly diſcouered.</p>
            <p>By L. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To the R<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> VVorshipfull Syr Humphry Lynde.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eccleſ 7. v. 30.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Solummodo hoc inueni, quod fecerit Deus hominem rectum; Et ipſe ſe infinitis miſcuerit quaestionibus.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Permiſſu Superiorum. M.DC.XXIIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21663:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:21663:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL Syr Humphry Lynde.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>YR</hi> It may be you will take it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindly to ſee vnawares your ſelfe and your papers thus in print. But I was moued to doe it by due co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of that which follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. I receaued them not as ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, neyther do I thinke you gaue them to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed. You wrote againſt a printed Catalogue of Catholike Profeſſors, wherof a deare friend of mine is the Author, giuen you vpon a former Conference which your ſelf procured betweene ſome other of my Friends and your Doctors, concerning a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Catalogue; which Conference though pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatly inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, was afterwards victoriouſly printed. Wherefore writing them as you did, againſt ſuch a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21663:3"/>
Booke, and vpon ſuch an occaſion, you might eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thinke they would be anſwered; and it is not ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge they ſhould come to be printed. As the great opinion which others had of your deepe learning, and your owne profeſſion of your great skill and reading in the Fathers, made me diligently to peruſe thoſe authorityes alleadged by you: ſo hauing well examined them, I thought my ſelfe diuers wayes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliged to giue a large &amp; full Reply vnto them. And being as you are moſt extremely, and moſt veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſtant in opinion from me; no maruell, if to be better vnderſtood, I ſpeak ſo lowd that all the Land may heare me. And for the ſame cauſe you muſt pardon me, if I rather chooſe to expoſe both you &amp; my ſelfe to the iudgment of others, then hauing ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome little paynes in this matter to make you the only iudge of my labours. The old <hi>Maister Buggs</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing carried away with <hi>Ecce in Penetralibus,</hi> thinketh to haue found the Meſſias in your ſtudy, and was wholy tranſported with thoſe choſen places, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected authorities contayned in your papers; which tending to no leſſe then the loſſe of his ſoule, meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted great compaſſion: the like may happen to others which deſerueth preuention. Your owne Doctors haue already adorned the Pageant of their victory with the publication of your Names: Vnto you is giuen the driuing on of the Chariot: and the old <hi>Maister Buggs</hi> is led in Triumph. Some perchance haue been taken in the net of the Title, and may be freed againe by the net of Chriſt; which therefore
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21663:3"/>
ſhould not hange in the Riuers of priuate papers, when the other flyeth in the ayre, but ſhould be caſt into the Sea of the wide World, to gather and draw togeather all kind of fiſhes. In this net the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhers themſelues are happily taken, and all they that are not taken, are loſt for euer. The other of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes is but a net to catch flyes, which though cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly wrought, muſt in tyme be ſwept away to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather with the Spiders. They haue printed againſt vs, and renewed an old Decree againſt our printing: if no Reply ſhould be made, ſome of them would thinke, that now they might lye by Proclamation. What greater ſigne of falſhood, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hauing told your owne tale to ſeeke to ſtop the mouthes of your Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries with old Statutes? But the State neuer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to make a Law againſt God, his Word will not be tyed. All Princes ſhould ſerue it, and all printing Preſſes muſt be ſubiect vnto it. Therfore no maruell, if the taking of one Preſſe do ſet two more on worke, and that your Doctors by ſeeking to ſuppreſſe the Truth, do preſſe it forward. You know then what moued me to diuulge your papers giuing the Fathers their due. I haue told you your owne, but ſparingly; and if you knew my hart, you would ſee, and confeſſe that I had done it friendly, <hi>Belieue, and you ſhall vnderstande,</hi> Belieue the Fathers and you ſhall vnderſtand the Fathers, <hi>He that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not the viſible vniuerſall Church, is no better then a Heathen,</hi> and belieueth neyther Church nor Fathers: but the <hi>vnlearned</hi> not knowing the doctrine of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21663:4"/>
Church and the <hi>vnstable</hi> forſaking that which they haue knowne, as they <hi>peruerte the Scriptures,</hi> ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo they preuert the Fathers <hi>to their owne damnation:</hi> from the which I beſeech God deliuer you, praying you likewiſe to thinke no otherwiſe of me, then as of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your vnfaygned Friend, and ſeruant in Chriſt. <hi>L. D.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:21663:4"/>
            <head>THE AVTHORITIES ALLEADGED BY <hi>Syr Humphry Lynde,</hi> agaynſt the <hi>Appendix.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Myracles.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>PIPHANIVS conuinceth not <hi>Ebion</hi> of falſe beliefe, becauſe neyther he nor any of his faction had the gift of working Miracles, but becauſe <hi>Ebion</hi> lykened himſelfe to Chriſt for his Circumciſion, and for his Birth: and he anſwers him, he could not be lyke to God, for that he was but a mortall Man, and was not able to rayſe <hi>Lazarus</hi> out of the graue, nor heale the ſicke &amp;c. If he would be lykened to Chriſt, he bid him to doe thoſe things; the which things, if he had required at <hi>Epiphanius</hi> hands, I thinke noe man but would haue doubted of the performance of them.—</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>—Read the place at large, and you shall find it hath no ſuch mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as is heere alleadged.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Myracles were neceſſary before the world belieued, to induce it to belieue, and he that ſeeketh to be confirmed by wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders now, is to be wondred at moſt of all himſelf, in refuſing to belieue what all the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieueth
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21663:5"/>
beſides himſelfe. <hi>De Ciuit. Dei, lib.</hi> 22. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. <hi>in principio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Shewed to be falſified.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now we for our parts, ſay not, that we muſt be belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that we are in the Church of Chriſt, becauſe <hi>Optatus</hi> or <hi>Ambroſe</hi> hath commended this wherein we are, or els becauſe that in all places of the world where our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted, there are ſo many Myracles wrought of healing diſeaſes &amp;c. For all theſe things that are done in the Catholike Church, are approued in aſmuch as they are done in the Catholike: <hi>And not that it is therfore Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, becauſe ſuch things are done there. August. de vnitat. Eccleſ. cap.</hi> 16.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tertullian.</hi> They will ſay (ſayth he) to excuſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues for hauing followed Hereſy: that their Doctours haue confirmed the Fayth of their Doctrine: that they haue rayſed vp the dead, reſtored the ſicke, foretould things to come, ſo as they were worthily taken for Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. As if (ſayth he) this were not written, that many ſhould come working great Myracles, to fortify the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfullnes of their corrupt preaching. <hi>De Praeſcrip. cap.</hi> 44.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Hierome.</hi> The Galathians had the gift of Healing, and of Propheſy, and yet they were inſnared by the falſe Prophets; and it is to be obſerued, that powers and ſignes are ſeene to be wrought in thoſe that hold not the Truth of the Ghoſpell, which may be ſayd agaynſt the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, that think their Fayth is ſufficiently proued if they haue wrought any Myracle, who in the day of Iudgment, ſhall deſerue to heare this ſaying: <hi>I know you not, depart from me. In Epiſt. ad Galat. cap.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Augustine.</hi> Let no man ſell you fables. <hi>Pontius</hi> hath wrought a Myracle. <hi>Donatus</hi> hath prayed, and God hath anſwered him from Heauen. Firſt, either they are decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, or ſo deceaue. <hi>In Ioan. tract.</hi> 13. <hi>Et cont. Fauſtum Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nichaum. lib.</hi> 13. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. <hi>Et de Ciuit. Dei, lib.</hi> 20. <hi>cap.</hi> 19.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwered, Sect.</hi> 5.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:21663:5"/>
               <head>Of Iuſtification by Fayth only.</head>
               <p>THis is the worke of God, that he which belieueth in Chriſt, ſhould be ſaued without workes; freely (by <hi>Grace</hi> only) receauing the pardon of his ſinnes. <hi>Amb. cap.</hi> 1. <hi>in Corinth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What is the Law of Fayth? Euen to be ſaued by Grace. Heere the Apoſtle ſheweth the goodnes of God, who not only ſaueth vs, but alſo iuſtifieth and glorifieth vs, vſing no workes heerunto, but requyring (<hi>Fayth</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.) <hi>Chryſ. Hom.</hi> 7. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Baſil.</hi> This is true and perfect reioycing in God, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a man is not lifted vp with his owne righteouſnes, but knoweth himſelfe to be voyd of true righteouſnes, and to be iuſtified by (<hi>Fayth</hi> only) in Chriſt. <hi>Homil. de humil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theodoret.</hi> We haue not belieued of our owne accord, but being called we came; and being come, he exacteth not purity &amp; innocency of life at our hands, but by (<hi>Faith</hi> only) he forgaue our ſinnes. <hi>Coment.</hi> 2. <hi>Eph.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bernard.</hi> Whoſoeuer is touched with his ſinnes, and hungreth after rightneouſnes: Let him belieue in God, that iuſtifieth ſinners, and being iuſtified by (<hi>Fayth</hi> only) he ſhall haue peace with God. <hi>Cant. Serm.</hi> 22.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwered, Sect.</hi> 6.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Free-will.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>BEllarmine.</hi> Man before all Grace, hath Free-will, not to things morall and naturall, but euen to the works of piety, and things ſupernaturall. <hi>De Grat. &amp; lib. Arbit. l.</hi> 6. <hi>cap. vltim.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Baſil.</hi> There is nothing left in thee O man, to be proud off, who muſt mortify all that is thy owne, and ſeeke for life to come in Chriſt, the firſt fruits wherof we haue
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21663:6"/>
already attayned in Chriſt; <hi>owing all, euen that we liue, to the Grace and gift of God.</hi> For it is God that giueth both the Will, and the Deed, according to his good pleaſure. <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil. conc. de humil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bernard.</hi> To will, is in vs by Free-will, but not to performe nor will. I ſay, not to will eyther good or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, but only to will; for, <hi>To will good, is a gift of Grace,</hi> to will euill, is a defect. Free-will maketh vs well-willing, from Free-will we haue power to will, but to will well cometh of grace. <hi>De Grat. &amp; lib. Arb.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> It is certaine that we are willing when we are ſo, but it is he that maketh vs ſo, of whome it is ſayd, It is God that worketh the will in vs: It is certayne that we worke when we doe ſo, but it is he that giueth vs this working power, by adding vnto our will, moſt effectuall ſtrength, as if he ſayd, I will make you work. <hi>De bono perſeuer. cap.</hi> 13.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Falſe cited, and shewed to be falſified.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Idem.</hi> Except God firſt make vs to be willing, and then worke with vs being willing, we ſhall neuer bring to paſſe any good worke. <hi>De Grat. &amp; lib. Arbit cap.</hi> 16.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Idem.</hi> We muſt confeſſe, that we haue Free-will, both to good and euill, but in doing euill, euery man, iuſt and vniuſt is free, but in doing good, none can be free, in Will &amp; Act, vnles he be freed by him that ſayd; <hi>If the Sonne free you, you are truely freed. De Corrept. &amp; Gra. cap.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> We will, but it is God that worketh in vs to will; we worke, but it is God that worketh in vs to worke, according to his good pleaſure. This is behoof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for vs both to belieue and ſpeake. This is a true Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, that our Confeſſion may be humble and lowly, and that God may haue the whole: we liue more in safty, if we giue all vnto God, rather then if we commit our ſelues, partly to our ſelues, and partly to him. <hi>August. de
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21663:6"/>
bono perſeuer. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Falſe cited.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> Farre be it from the Children of promiſe, that they ſhould ſay: Behold, without thee we can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare our owne harts; let none ſo thinke but thoſe that are proud defenders of their owne Freewill, and forſakers of the Catholike Fayth: for as no man can begin any good without God, ſo no man can perfect good with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God. <hi>Contr. duas Epiſtol. Pelag. lib.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> Why doe we preſume too much of the power of Nature? It is wounded, maimed, vexed, and loſt: let vs confeſſe it freely, and not defend it falſely; therefore let vs ſeeke Gods Grace, not to forme, but to reforme it thereby. <hi>De Natur. &amp; Grat. cap.</hi> 35.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Falſe cited.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Non volentis, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> currentis, ſed miſcrentis eſt Dei, vt totum Deo detur, qui hominis voluntatem bonam &amp; praeparat adiuuan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, &amp; adiuuat praeparatam.</hi> Auguſt. Enchir. ad Laurent. cap. 32.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwered, Sect.</hi> 7.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Sacrament.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CYprian.</hi> The Bread which our Lord gaue to his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples, not in Shape, but in Subſtance or Nature, changed by the Omnipotency, of the Word, is made Fleſh.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The words of <hi>Cyprian</hi> are, <hi>Panis non effigie, ſed na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura mutatus &amp;c.</hi> which you haue tranſlated in Subſtance or Nature: where there is no word of Subſtance in <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The Chapter of <hi>Coena Domini,</hi> where this place is vrged, is none of <hi>Cyprians. Extat inter opera Cypriani Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo de Coena Domini, qui Cypriani Epiſcopi Carthaginenſis eſſe non videtur (inquit Bellarminus) lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Euchar. cap.</hi> 9. <hi>Author
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21663:7"/>
Sermonis de Coena Domini, non est Cyprianus, ſed aliquis posterior. Bellarm. lib. de Euchar.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 26. <hi>Author Sermonis de Coena Domini, eſt ignotus, inquit Garetius. De veritate Corporis Christi. fol.</hi> 181.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cyprian.</hi> The Lord in his laſt Supper wherin he did participate with his Apoſtles, gaue Bread and Wine with his owne hands: but he gaue his Body to be crucified on the Croſſe, to the hands of his ſouldiars &amp;c. <hi>Vt diuerſa no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina vel ſpecies ad vnam reducerentur eſſentiam, &amp; ſignificantia &amp; ſignificata ijſdem vocabulis cenſerentur. De Vnctione Chriſmatis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Shewed to be falſified.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereunto you adde, pag 47. in the Margent. <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian; Hoc est corpus meum, hoc eſt figura corporis mei. cont. Marci. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Aug. Chriſtus figuram Corporis ſui Diſcipulis com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendauit. In Pſal.</hi> 3. <hi>Ambroſ. de Sacram. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. <hi>Hier. ad verb. Iouin. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Aug. in Leuit. quaest.</hi> 57. <hi>Gelaſius cont. Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichem. Aug. de Doctr. Christian. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 16. It is a figure commaunding vs to lay vp in our Remembrance, that his Fleſh was crucified and wounded for vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwered Sect.</hi> 8. <hi>&amp; ſequent.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:21663:7"/>
            <head>A DEFENCE OF THE APPENDIX. TO THE RIGHT Worshipfull Syr Humphry Lynde.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Section I.</hi> The Fisher freed, and the Catcher catcht. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the firſt point of the <hi>Appendix,</hi> shewing the continuall Viſibility of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our owne Doctors in your owne houſe profeſſed, as you know, <hi>The true Church muſt be able to name Profeſſors in all Ages;</hi> &amp; made it the very grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of their Argument, in that Diſpute. Wherefore in all reaſon, before you went about to anſwere the Booke, which you receaued of the Catalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue of our Profeſſors, you ſhould haue giuen another, or referred vs to ſome booke of an other of yours. And that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21663:8"/>
ſo much the more, becauſe hitherto ſuch a Catalogue on your ſide hath byn held impoſſible to be found, made, or produced. And hauing beene euermore demaunded and required for a hundred yeares togeather, could neuer as yet be ſeene nor obtayned.</p>
               <p>Certainly, thoſe your Champions which were choſen by your ſelfe, and with great expectation vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke to doe it, when they came to the Tryall, perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med nothing; and all that they did, was but cunningly to auoyde the Queſtion, giuen in theſe expreſſe termes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whether the Protestant Church was in all Ages viſible, eſpecially in the Ages before Luther; and whether the Names of ſuch viſible Proteſtants in all Ages can be shewed, and proued out of good Authors?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherein euery man may ſee, there was nothing els demaunded, but a playne Catalogue or Table, of the Names of your Profeſſors in all Ages proued by good Authors. According wherunto, they receaued alſo ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paper before the meeting, which there was publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly read, that ech partie ſhould produce their Catalogues out of good Authors, and then interchangably by termes defend them. But this Table or Catalogue of the names of our Profeſſors ſeemed a Lyon in the way of your Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, which therefore they durſt not come neere nor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, but ſought by diuers ſtraines to eſchew it, and to turne the eyes and eares of the audience from their expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of it.</p>
               <p>As firſt they ſought to make two Queſtions of the Queſtion propounded; and flying the latter part, inſteed of ſhewing the viſibility of their Church, they would haue proued it <hi>à Priori</hi> (as they tearmed it) without ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their viſible Paſtors, which was the poynt demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
               <p>Secondly, they deride their Aduerſaries, for demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Names of their Profeſſors, as if they had imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently called <hi>for a Buttry Booke,</hi> of the Names of thoſe,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21663:8"/>
that euer were admitted into the Church of Chriſt; irregi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly comparing the Hiſtories of the Church wherein the Names of her Biſhops, Martyrs, and other holy Men, were carefully recorded, to Buttry Bookes of Names. And for the ſame cauſe calling their Aduerſaries <hi>Nominalls,</hi> they boaſted themſelues to be <hi>Realls;</hi> as if their Aduerſaries had demaunded, no Men, but only Names of Men: or as if the Profeſſors of the true Faith, like Knights Errants, or thoſe of the round Table, had been no reall Men at all, but only names; which is aſmuch to ſay, as that the Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories of the Church were meere fables.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, they ſought to flinch by propounding ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry tymes, diuers other Queſtions to be diſputed. Which was, as it were, to put vp many Hares before the Hou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, thereby to conceale the Kennell of that Fox which was then hunted.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, they endeauoured to diuert the Queſtion, from prouing themſelues the true Church, by naming the viſible Profeſſors therof in all Ages, which was the thing demaunded; to proue the ſame by aſſuming they held the truth, that is to ſay, in euery particular Controuerſie; as for Example, in denying of Tranſubſtantiation, Merits of Works and the like. Which was as plaine a <hi>Tranſition,</hi> as if in caſe the Queſtion had byn about Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, their Aduerſaries ſhould haue gone about to proue it, by prouing themſelues to be the true Church that held it. For both theſe kinde of proofes by a remote <hi>Medium</hi> do euidently transferre the Queſtion; the one from a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall to a particular point, which was your Doctors fault: the other from a particuler to a generall, as in the other Example.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, being called vpon by the Hearers, and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially by the Proteſtants themſelues, which were ten to one, and confided much in their owne cauſe, to giue the Names of their Profeſſors in all Ages; they named only Chriſt and his Apoſtles, with others, one or two
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21663:9"/>
more of the firſt Age alone. Which according to the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion vndertaken, they ſhould haue proued to be Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, by naming Proteſtants that ſucceeded them in all Ages following; but ſeeking euermore to auoyde that Rocke, they would haue ſtayed there, and before they went any further, vrged to proue the Profeſſors of the firſt Age to be Proteſtants, not by naming their Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, but by examining their Doctrine; Which againe had been to diuerte from the matter, and to runne from the generall point then in Queſtion, to all particular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies.</p>
               <p>Sixtly; Therefore when none of theſe deuiſes could ſatisfy the expectation of the Hearers, fearing as it ſeemed, leaſt, according to the words of the Queſtion and playne intention of that meeting, they ſhould haue byn vrged againe by the Hearers, to ſet downe a full Catalogue of all Ages, as once before they were importuned to doe, they ſuddenly brake off, and ſo departed.</p>
               <p>Seauenthly; My L. <hi>of Warwicke</hi> imagining percha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that this proceeded not ſo much from lacke of ability, as from want of due preparation, on their behalfe promiſed a Catalogue within 2. or 3. dayes, which though ſought agayne by letter, neuer yet appeared.</p>
               <p>Eightly; The Anſwerers themſelues repayred the next day to your owne houſe, agayne offering to deliuer their Catalogue with one hand, ſo they might receaue yours with the other. Which another ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding by, whome they alſo tooke to be a Proteſtant Miniſter, affirmed to be very reaſonable and indifferent. But you anſwered, You knew their minde for that point, and that they would neuer doe it, before the Names of the firſt Age were tryed, and ſo of the reſt in order.</p>
               <p>Ninthly; a printed Catalogue was ſent to your ſelfe in particuler, hoping it might ſerue as an engine to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portune, and as it were to extort another from you, or from your Doctours. But all in vayne, which maketh
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21663:9"/>
many much to feare, that this Catalogue of your Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, will neuer be produced, and conſequently that your Church, cannot poſſible be the true Church of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>And now no maruell if ſome of the Hearers, when they ſaw the Booke of <hi>The Fisher catched in his owne Net,</hi> writen as it were in triumph of your victory in that Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute, compared it to thoſe other Puritan Bookes, which haue been lately printed of the great victories of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants in their Warres againſt the Catholiks beyond the Seas: whereas in truth, not the Catholikes, but the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants themſelues, haue beene alwayes notoriouſly van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed and ouerthrowne. And preſuming it came forth from his owne fingers that hath the principall part ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, they ſpare not to ſay, that it better deſerued to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>The feates, and lyes of Doctor Feat-Lye,</hi> then the other Title; which in falſhood well agreeing with the Booke it ſelfe in that reſpect alone, might iuſtly ſeeme a fit lace or facing for it. For beſides the ſundry ſhifts and ſlights of the Doctors contayned in it, they accuſe it alſo of many groſſe vntruthes without end or number; in relating things out of due place and order, to their owne aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage; in daubing and amplifying the ſpeeches of D. <hi>Featly</hi> with much addition, and ſubſtraction of matter: As for Example.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That <hi>M. Bugges,</hi> the old Gentleman, who firſt deſired the former Diſpute, was ſicke, and ſolicited in his ſicknes by ſome Papiſts about him to forſake his Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: And that it was feared he would haue fallen from his Fayth, if he had not recouered of his ſicknes: which is altogeather falſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That he was much confirmed in his Religion, by hearing the former Diſputation: which vnleſſe he did extreamly forget himſelf (hauing often ſayd the contrary) is alſo falſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That you <hi>Syr Humfrey,</hi> found <hi>M. Fisher</hi> by chance
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21663:10"/>
in <hi>Drurie Lane;</hi> whereas you know, you came of purpoſe to offer him a friendly Conference with D. <hi>White.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. That M. <hi>Fisher</hi> hauing written the Queſtion, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnder his owne hand, he would anſwere vpon it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiuely, <hi>As challenging and expecting Oppoſers;</hi> which was falſe, for he was firſt asked by your ſelf, whether he would oppoſe or anſwere: wherupon he wrote he would an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That you <hi>Syr Humfrey,</hi> tould <hi>M. Buggs,</hi> if M. <hi>Fisher</hi> would come with foure, or ſix at the moſt, they ſhould be admitted for his ſake, whereas it was expreſſely agreed on, that <hi>D. White</hi> and M. <hi>Fisher,</hi> ſhould only bring an Aſſiſtant, foure Witneſſes, and a Writer, and no more, with each of them, and that the matter ſhould be kept ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, thereby to make the meeting very priuate. Which M. <hi>Fisher</hi> duly obſerued, but when he came he found the houſe full of Proteſtants contrary to former agreement.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That <hi>D. White</hi> and <hi>D. Featly,</hi> being inuited by you to Dinner, and ſtaying a while after Dinner, had notice giuen them (as it were by chance) that ſome Ieſuits were in the next roome, ready to confer with them, and that the Doctors were at laſt perſwaded to haue ſome Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with them. As if forſooth they had neuer heard of the meeting before; when the truth is, that ſome daies before, <hi>D. White</hi> had receaued the Queſtion, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke to oppoſe agaynſt it, though afterward for more ſecurity he vſed <hi>D. Featly</hi> for his Champion, and both of them came thither of purpoſe, to make good the former challenge.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The Queſtion was falſely and ſophiſtically prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, by putting into the midſt therof the figure of (2) in fauour of the Oppoſer, who ſought to make it a dubble Queſtion.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Before the Diſputation began, <hi>D. Featly</hi> hauing propounded many other poynts of Controuerſie to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert the Queſtion, That <hi>M. Sweete</hi> ſhould anſwere they
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21663:10"/>
were ſcholaſticall poynts not fundamentall. Which was not ſo; only he affirmed they were nothing to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. Which he was moued the rather to ſay, becauſe a little before he had deſired two things of the Auditorie. 1. That all bitter ſpeeches might be forborne. And 2. that nothing might be heard or ſpoken which was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the Queſtion.</p>
               <p n="9">9. That M. <hi>Fisher</hi> being charged to haue ſlaundred Doctor <hi>White</hi> in a former Conference, anſwered no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: which is falſe, for he ſtood vp, and ſolemnely proteſted vpon his Conſcience, that he neuer ſlaundred him.</p>
               <p n="10">10. And againe, that being charged to anſwere vpon his Conſcience, whether he belieued Chriſt and his Apoſtles taught the Proteſtant faith, he refuſed to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere. Which is meerely falſe. It is true, that <hi>D. Featly</hi> before he began to diſpute, coniured <hi>M. Fisher</hi> after an inſolent manner, to anſwere according to his conſcience, which <hi>M. Fisher</hi> accepted, and wiſhed him to doe the like.</p>
               <p>I omit many other ſuch <hi>Feates,</hi> which the Hearers when they read, affirmed to be plaine <hi>Lyes,</hi> from whome ſoeuer they proceeded. If the Doctors according to their vndertaking, had giuen a ſufficient and full Catalogue of their Profeſſors in all Ages, <hi>The Fisher had beene taken indeed in his owne Net,</hi> and caught in the Queſtion which himſelf propounded; but contrarily hauing taken more vpon them then they were able to performe, and not being able to ſet downe the Catalogue, which according to the iſſue of the Queſtion was then expected, the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors themſelues were manifeſtly taken in the Net of the Fiſher. Wherein, by profeſſing as they did, that, <hi>The true Church muſt be able to Name Profeſſors in all Ages,</hi> they haue ſo intangled themſelues, that howſoeuer they may dance in this Net to their owne ſhame and confuſion, they can neuer get out, vntill they name them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:21663:11"/>And now to come home againe to your ſelfe (endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoring in the meane tyme as you doe to ouerthrow the ſucceſſion of their Church, and not being able to ſhew another of yours) what do you get, or what do you ſeeke therby, but only the ruine and demoliſhment, both of your Church and theirs, leauing no true Church vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth, which cannot ſubſiſt without a viſible ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Profeſſors to be named in all Ages, as you and your Doctors haue vrged? And by conſequence, for wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of ſuch a viſible Church, you leaue no true Fayth at all, nor true Religion in the world. <hi>And who is a Naturall, but he that denyes it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore to conclude this Section, your Doctors with a great deale of noyſe, hauing filled the aire with nothing but ſmoke. If now their Aduerſaries ſhould turne their owne Ordinance againſt them and reaſon thus, it is not your valor that would be able to defend them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Church that is Catholike as it ought to be, or the Church whoſe fayth is Eternall, or the Church of Christ and his Apostles, must be able to name Succeſsors in all Ages. But the Proteſtant Church is not able to name the Profeſsors of their Fayth, nor the Succeſſors therein, to Christ and his Apostles in all Ages.</hi> Ergo, <hi>the Protestant Church is not Catholike as it ought to be, nor the Church whoſe Fayth is eternall, nor the Church of Christ and his Apoſtles.</hi> The <hi>Maior</hi> is their owne, and publickly produced by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The <hi>Minor</hi> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be denyed vntill the Names be ſhewed. Wherefore vntill this Fort be built, how can you defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d them, or where will you hide them from the power of this Gun-ſhot? And yet as this worke is plainly impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to be rayſed or performed, ſo it is no leſſe impoſſible, that the Proteſtants ſhould be found the true Church, &amp; by Conſequence, that any may be ſaued remayning in it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:21663:11"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Section II.</hi> In reference to a ſecond point of the <hi>Appendix,</hi> shewing their Conuerſions in all Ages.</head>
               <p>HAD you giuen vs ſuch another Catalogue of your Profeſſors, as you receaued of theirs, to make your party good agaynſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, you ſhould haue ſhewed the like Conuerſions of Heathen Nations to the Fayth of Chriſt by your Miniſters in all Ages; as that Booke hath ſhewed, by their Apoſtolicall Preachers. And that eſpecially after thoſe tymes wherin you pretend their Church was fallen, and the ſpirit of God was departed from them. As for Example, in the third Age were conuerted Donaldus King of Scotland, his Wife, Children, and Nobility. The Court of the Prince of Arabia, pag. 20. In the fourth Age, the Beſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, Dacians, Getes, and Scythians, pag. 26. In the fifth Age, the Sarazens, the Scots, the Iriſh, pag. 32. In the ſixt Age, the Pictes, the Gothes, the Bauarians, the Engliſh, pag. 36. 38. In the ſeauenth Age, diuers Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uians, the Weſtphalians, and many of our Nation, Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Teiſterbandia, of Weſtphalia, of Holland, the King and Queene of Perſia, with forty thouſand Perci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, pag. 42 44. In the eight Age, Saxons, Borucluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, the Friſians, the Haſſits, the Thuringians, the Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, the Erphordians, two Saxon Dukes, pag. 48. In the ninth Age, the Danes, Swethens, and people of Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tania, the whole Iland of the Rugians, the Bulgarians, the Ruthens, or Ruſſians, pag. 52. 54. In the tenth Age, Worziuous the laſt Pagan Duke in Bohemia, the King of Norway, the Polonians, the Sclauonians, and Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garians, Heraldus King of the Danes, and Sueno his Sonne, pag. 60. In the eleuenth Age, the Pruſſians, the Vindians, alſo Pannonians and Tranſiluanians, the lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21663:12"/>
Hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>garians, pag. 64. 68. In the twelfe Age, the Pome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranians, the people of Norway, Magnus King of the Gothes, pag. 70. 72. In the thirteenth Age, the Liuoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, the Lituanians, innumerable Tartarians, pag. 76. 78. In the fourtenth Age, the Canary Ilandes, the Chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, the Lipnenſians, Boſnians, Patrinians, and other Sclauonian Nations, pag. 84. In the fifteenth Age, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogeſsians, the Kingdomes of Bentomine, Guinaea, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gola, and Congo, Zerra Iacob Emperour of the Abiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyns, pag. 90. In the ſixteenth Age, the Kingdome of Manicongo in Africa, the Kings of Amanguntium and Bungo, innumerable Indians, Iaponians, Braſilians, and other Weſterne and Orientall people, more Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries and Kingdomes then all Chriſtendome before. In the ſeaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teenth Age, the King of Sarra Leaena in the Eaſt Indies, with his Brethren and Children, beſides many other in China, Iaponia, Perſia, and other Nations.</p>
               <p>This Argument taken from the <hi>great increaſe of fruit which continueth, and abideth among them, Ioan.</hi> 15. 16. and from the wonderfull propagation of their Religion, not only in the firſt fiue hundred yeares after Chriſt, but alſo much more in the Ages following to this preſent tyme; is ſurely a moſt forcible and ſtrong perſwaſion, that they alone among all other ſortes of Chriſtians, are the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and people whome God had bleſſed. Haue Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters been choſen and preſerued by Almighty God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his owne Seruants, to perſwade in the force of his word innumerable people from tyme to tyme, to renou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and tread vnder their feete the Auncient Gods of their Forefathers, in whome they ſo much confided; and to receaue him for their true and only God, who whipped and crowned with thornes, was nayled to a Croſſe in the ſight of the world, and ſo dyed? Haue all theſe ſeuerall Countries and Kingdomes, ſo extremely different in cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mats, in tongues, in affections, in cuſtomes, and in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures beene voluntarily reduced to the vnity of one and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21663:12"/>
and the ſame Fayth in Chriſt, and to the obedience of one Paſtor vnder Chriſt, by the followers of Antichriſt? Haue the limmes of the Diuell reformed the ſauage, bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh, and wicked manners of ſo many People and Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, changing their hartes, and bringing them vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their knees, to ſerue their Creator, with piety and humility, and in exerciſe of all kind of vertue?</p>
               <p>Then I muſt needes confeſſe, it ſeemeth vnto me, that eyther God himſelfe muſt be in loue with Idolatry, or Chriſt himſelfe muſt become Antichriſt, or the Diuell himſelfe hauing forſaken his malice, is now changed to be a ſeruant of Chriſt. Neyther do I ſee how poſſibly you can deny theſe innumerable Nations to haue beene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted by the true Church, recommended vnto vs in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture, vnleſſe we deny both Church and Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture. For by theſe Conuerſions of Nations in all Ages, your Aduerſaries doe manifeſtly proue themſelues to be that Church which muſt in the end conuert all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and was therefore ſurnamed Catholike or Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall. And thereby it cannot be denyed they make it moſt apparent (the promiſes thereof in the Law, <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.17. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. In the <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 71.6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 21. <hi>&amp;</hi> 28. In the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2.2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 60. <hi>&amp;</hi> 61. <hi>&amp;</hi> 62. <hi>Hier.</hi> 33. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 33.22. <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.44. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In the old and new Teſtament, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 28.19. <hi>Luc.</hi> 24.47. being ſo euidently performed by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) that they alone are the ſpirituall ſeede of Abraham, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.13. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. The inheritance of the Sonne of God, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 47. The Mountaine on the toppe of Mountaines, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.12. The Mountaine fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the world, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.44. The glorious Citty, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 86. whoſe gates muſt be alwayes open, that the ſtrength of the Gentiles &amp; their Kings may be brought vnto it: and the Nation and Kingdome, that will not ſerue it, muſt periſh, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.11.12. That bleſſed Company <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.9. whome our Sauiour promiſed to aſſiſt all dayes, or euery day, teaching and baptizing all Nations vnto the end of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21663:13"/>
the world. <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. <hi>&amp;</hi> 24. Heere againe (as in the end the former Section) if they ſhould argue Syllogiſtically againſt your Doctors in this manner, though you had the ſtrength of Hercules, I think you would hardly be able to defend them. <hi>That Church which conuerted Nations in all Ages, is the true Church of Christ and his Apostles, recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto vs, in holy Scripture. But the Catholike, and not the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Church, hath conuerted Nations in all Ages.</hi> Ergo, <hi>the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike, and not the Protestant Church, is the true Church of Christ and his Apoſtles, recommended vnto vs in holy Scripture.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Section III.</hi> In reference to a third point of the <hi>Appendix,</hi> shewing their Religion to haue byn confirmed by Myracles in all Ages.</head>
               <p>HAd you giuen vs a view of ſo many Nations reduced to the Faith of Chriſt by your Profeſſors as he hath named conuerted by theirs, that your Church might not appeare altogeather inferior to theirs, you ſhould haue ſhewed ſome points of your Religion confirmed by Myracles againſt them, as that Booke hath declared many points of theirs in all Ages, miraculouſly authorized, and as it were ſubſcribed by the hand of God againſt you; &amp; thoſe ſo euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly teſtified not only by Auncient Hiſtories, but alſo by the holy Fathers themſelues, not liable to any exception, in the firſt fiue hundred yeares &amp; downewards, as they ſeeme to enforce all good Chriſtians to belieue them.</p>
               <p>As for Example, in the ſecond Age, <hi>Narciſsus</hi> Biſhop of Hieruſalem, turned water into Oyle for the vſe of the Church, <hi>Euſebius lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Cap.</hi> 8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 9. <hi>S. Balbina</hi> and her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſtored to health by touching the Chaynes wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21663:13"/>
with Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> was bound, <hi>Baron. An.</hi> 132. <hi>n.</hi> 2. Cures wrought by the Bodies and Sepulchers of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs. <hi>Iustin. quast.</hi> 28.</p>
               <p>In the third Age, the Myracles of <hi>S. Gregorie</hi> the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-worker, &amp; ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wrought by the ſigne of the Croſſe, <hi>Niſſen. in vita Greg. Thau.</hi> And S. <hi>Baſil. de Sp. Sanct. cap.</hi> 29. Alſo Myracles confirming the <hi>Euchariſt, &amp; Reall Preſence. Cyp. ſer. de Lapſis.</hi> Alſo S. <hi>Cecily</hi> ſhewed to <hi>Vale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> the Angell Guardian of her virginitie. <hi>Metaphraſtes</hi> and <hi>Surius</hi> in her life.</p>
               <p>In the fourth Age, a ſicke Woman cured, and a dead Bodie reſtored to life, by the wood of the Holy Croſſe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it was firſt found out by Queene <hi>Helen. Ruffin. Hist. lib.</hi> 10. <hi>Cap.</hi> 7. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8. <hi>&amp; Seuer. Sulpit. Hiſt. ſacra lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Paul. Epiſt.</hi> 11. <hi>Niceph. lib.</hi> 8. The ſame myraculouſly multiplyed to ſatisfy the deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the world. <hi>Paul. Ep.</hi> 11. <hi>Cyr. catech.</hi> 10. Many other Myracles wrought by Reliques, <hi>Chryſ. orat. cont. Gentes.</hi> By holy-Water, <hi>Epiph. haer.</hi> 30. By adoration of the Bleſſed Sacrament, <hi>Naz. orat.</hi> 11. By prayers to our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, <hi>Nazian. in S. Cyp.</hi> By the merites of Martyrs. <hi>Ambroſ. ſerm.</hi> 91.</p>
               <p>In the fifth Age, many Myracles wrought by Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques of S. <hi>Stephen, Aug. lib.</hi> 22. <hi>de Ciuit. cap.</hi> 8. By the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gne of the Croſſe, <hi>Constantinus lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap</hi> 22. <hi>apud Surium, Tomo</hi> 4. by <hi>S. German.</hi> Alſo Myracles wrought by <hi>S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome,</hi> lying on his death bed, and after his deceaſe, the blinde, deafe, dumbe, and ſicke were cured: ſome by touching, ſome by kiſſing his Corpes, <hi>Euſebius Cremon. Ep. de morte eius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the ſixt Age, Myracles wrought to confirme the Sacrifice of the Maſſe, <hi>S. Greg. l.</hi> 4. <hi>Dial. cap.</hi> 57. and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Preſence, <hi>Euag. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Hiſt. cap.</hi> 35. <hi>Ioan. Diac. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de vita S. Greg. cap.</hi> 41. To confirme the honour and inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Saynts, <hi>Procop orat. de Edificat. Iustin. Euag. loco <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it. Greg. de Myrac. S. Martini l.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. 6. 7. The vſe of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21663:14"/>
in Proceſſions, and how by one of our Bleſſed Ladyes, painted by S. <hi>Luke,</hi> a contagious Peſtilence was diſpelled in Rome, <hi>Ciac. in Greg.</hi> 1. From another Image ſtabbed by a Iew, iſſued bloud, <hi>Greg. Turon. de glor. Mart. cap.</hi> 22. <hi>Sigeb. ann.</hi> 560. Holy Oyle flowed from a Croſſe, and from an Image of our Bleſſed Lady, curing many diſeaſes. <hi>Baron. ann.</hi> 564. Thus the Author of the Catalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue you receaued; And the like Myracles he ſheweth in the reſt of the ſucceeding Ages. As many more he might haue added aſwell in the firſt fiue hundred yeares as after, but that he thought it not neceſſary, and therefore ſpared the labour to recollect them.</p>
               <p>Which myraculous atteſtations, we muſt eyther be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue, and by conſequence muſt alſo confeſſe thoſe poynts of Religion confirmed by them, or els we ſhall not only condemne all Chriſtian Antiquity of lying, and belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of lyes, but muſt lykewiſe reiect all euidence of cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibility founded vpon human teſtimony; which is no leſſe then to deſtroy the very foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s both of Church, and Common-wealth, and all Society. Wherefore to binde this Burden alſo on your backe, that it may ſit the cloſſer, I will winde it vp in this manner. <hi>That Church whoſe Doctrine hath beene confirmed by Myracles in all Ages, is the true Church of Chriſt and his Apoſtles. But ſuch is the Doctrine of the Catholike, and not of the Protestant Church.</hi> Ergo, <hi>the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike, and not the Proteſtant Church, is the true Church of Christ and his Apostles.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:21663:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Section IIII.</hi> In reference to a fourth poynt of the <hi>Appendix,</hi> shewing the Doctrine of the Protestants to haue beene cenſured, and condemned by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in all Ages.</head>
               <p>HAd you likewiſe confirmed your Doctrine by ſuch diuine Authority, you ſhould haue ſhewed ſome one point of their Religion cenſured by any of the Fathers, or condemned by any law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Counſell, as that Booke quoteth aboue twenty of yours notoriouſly oppoſed and condemned by them.</p>
               <p>As for Example; Iuſtification by Fayth only, and Deniall of Iuſtice by Workes; condemned in Symon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus, <hi>Iren. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 20. Extrinſecall Iuſtice by imputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> only; in the Gnoſtickes, <hi>Iren. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. That no ſinne can hurt them that are indewed with Fayth; in Eunomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, <hi>Epiph. haer.</hi> 76. <hi>Aug. haer.</hi> 64. That ſinne abideth in the regenerate; condemned in Proclus, <hi>Epiph. haer.</hi> 64. That Baptiſme doth not waſhe away ſinne; condemned in the Meſſalians, <hi>Theod lib.</hi> 4. <hi>haer. fab.</hi> Neglect of the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of Baptiſme; condemned in Nouatus, <hi>Euſeb. lib.</hi> 6. Of holy Chriſme and the ſeale of our Lord (which is the ſigne of the Croſſe ſo called) condemned in Nouatus and his Diſciples, <hi>Theod. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>haer. fab.</hi> Deriſions of Exorciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, and Exufflations in Baptiſme; condemned in the Pelagians, <hi>Auguſt. de Nat. &amp; concupiſ. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 29. The Abſolution of Prieſts not auaileable, and the aboliſhment of Confeſſion; condemned in Nouatus and his Diſciples, <hi>Socrat. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 23. <hi>Cornel. apud Euſeb. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 43. <hi>Theod. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>haer. fab. Pacian. lib. aduerſ. eos.</hi> Denyall of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned Pennance; in the Audians, <hi>Theod. l.</hi> 4. <hi>haer. fab.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:21663:15"/>Denyall of the Reall Preſence; condemned in Iudas Iſcariot, <hi>Claud. Xanct. Rep.</hi> 2. <hi>de Eucha. cap.</hi> 14. <hi>Chryſ. hom.</hi> 46. <hi>in Ioan.</hi> 6. In the Simonians and Saturnians, <hi>Theod. Dial.</hi> 3. condemned likewyſe by <hi>Iren. l.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 34. <hi>post me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium.</hi> Impugning the reſeruation of the B. Sacrament; condemned in the Anthropomorphites, <hi>Cyr. ad Caloſyr.</hi> Denyall of Oblations, and Prayers for the Dead; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned in Aerius, <hi>Aug. haer.</hi> 53 <hi>Epiph. haer.</hi> 65. Denyall of Freewill; condemned in Symon Magus, <hi>Clem. Roman. Recog. lib.</hi> 3. In the Manichees, <hi>Aug. lib. cont. Fortunat. Manic.</hi> Ordination and Predeſtination to ſinne, and by conſequence, that God is the Author of ſinne; condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Predeſtinate, <hi>Sigeb.</hi> 415. <hi>Geneb. in Zoſimo.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned likewiſe in Symon Magus, <hi>Vin. Lirin. adu. prop. haeret. nouitat. cap.</hi> 34. And in Florinus, <hi>Euſeb. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 20. That Saynts are not to be inuocated; condemned in Vigilantius, <hi>Hier. cont. Vigil. cap.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. The Images of Chriſt and his Saynts not to be worſhipped; condemned in Xenaias; <hi>Niceph. lib.</hi> 16. <hi>cap.</hi> 27. Worſhip of Saints Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques to be Idolatry; condemned in Euſtachius, <hi>Socrat. l.</hi> 2 <hi>cap.</hi> 33. and condemned likewiſe in Vigilantius, <hi>Hier.</hi> 161.</p>
               <p>Impugnation of ſingle life, and vowed Chaſtity, and that Marriage is equall to Virginity; condemned in Heluidius, and Iouinian, <hi>Hier. cont. Heluid. &amp; Iouin.</hi> Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allowance of preſcript Faſts; condemned in Aerius, <hi>Epip. haer.</hi> 75. <hi>Auguſt. haer.</hi> 53. and in Euſtachius, <hi>Socrat. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 33. Noe difference of Merits in Heauen; condemned in Iouinian, <hi>Hier. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>aduerſ. Iouin.</hi> Good vſe of Riches, preferred before Euangelicall Pouerty; condemned in Vigilantius. <hi>S. Thom. opuſc.</hi> 17.</p>
               <p>Denyall of one Chiefe Paſtor in Earth; condemned in Nouatus, <hi>Euſeb. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 43. Denyall of vnwritten Traditions; condemned in the Valentinians, <hi>Tertul. lib. de Praeſc. &amp; hiſt. Eccleſ. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 16. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 36. That the viſible Catholike Church, might remaine in one parte,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21663:15"/>
and periſh in the reſt of the world; condemned in the Donatiſts, <hi>Aug. cont. lit. Petil. l.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 108. <hi>&amp; lib. de Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat. Eccleſ. cap.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp; per totum librum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus the Author of the Catalogue; whereunto if I ſhould adde out of the Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Apology page 74. and page 127. and pag. 207. how inſolently and impiouſly the moſt and beſt learned Proteſtant-writers doe like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe cenſure, and condemne the Fathers of the firſt fiue hundred yeares, I know you would be aſhamed to reade them. But this may ſuffice, to giue the Reader iuſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to admire the little conſcience of your late Engliſh Doctors, in challenging the Fathers of the firſt fiue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares, wherein if their Aduerſaries might come to an indifferent and equall tryall with them, the very <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles</hi> of the Fathers Books againſt them, were ſufficient to ouerthrow them. Only in this place I will giue the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this ſhort <hi>Notandum:</hi> for the which if he deſire ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely to know and belieue the Doctrine of the Fathers, he ſhall haue cauſe to thanke me. When any of the holy Fathers, do cenſure any poynt of Doctrine, taxing it of Hereſy, or noteth it as the particuler opinion of ſome Heretike, or reproueth it very much, or wondreth at it, eſpecially if it be ſuch a thing as euery learned Man may eaſily know, or was neceſſary to be taught, and that no other Father did therein oppoſe himſelf againſt him; It is an euident Teſtimony, that his Doctrine therein was the generall Doctrine of the Church at that tyme; and ought to be ſo receaued of the Ages that follow. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Author of that Booke, hauing ſhewed ſo many poynts of your Doctrine to haue beene ſo notoriouſly ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured and condemned by the Auncient Fathers of the firſt fiue hundred yeares in the Hetetikes of thoſe tymes, beſides many other poynts and ſome of thoſe alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by Fathers and Councells in after Ages (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto you haue not anſwered a word) it is for ought I can ſee, or perceaue, a cleare demonſtration, that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21663:16"/>
of thoſe tymes were theirs, and that, eyther your Profeſſors were none at all, or no other then thoſe, that were condemned by them.</p>
               <p>Thus, all things with them are infallibly certaine, eaſie to be knowne, and moſt conſpicuous. They fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the ſtreame and current of that Doctrine, which, by many knowne Succeſſions of holy and learned Men, Martyres, and Biſhops, as it were by ſo many Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nells, they deriue from Chriſt and his Apoſtles. They follow the fame and greatnes of that Church, which by conuerting Countries and Nations in all Ages, is become eminent and apparent aboue all other ſortes of Chriſtians, like a <hi>Citty vpon a Hill,</hi> aboue the Moale-hills; or like the <hi>Little Stone in Daniel,</hi> which growing to be a Mountaine, filleth the world with it's greatnes. They follow the ſecurity of thoſe Letters-Patents which the hand of God hath ſigned with his owne Seale, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended to the world, by Atteſtation of many My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles in confirmation of their Doctrine. And laſtly they follow the infallible and powerfull Authority of that Body, which by Ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſures of Doctors, &amp; Decrees of Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells from tyme to tyme hath euer confounded all thoſe that oppoſed themſelues againſt it; While you in the meane tyme, without any lineall Deſcente from thoſe whome you pretend to haue beene your Aunceſtors; without the Progenie of any Gentills conuerted by you; without any warrant of Gods hand, or ſentence of his Iudges for you, do ſtill remayne in the darcknes of your inuiſible Church, toſſed in the Sea of Error, <hi>with euery winde of new Doctrine,</hi> not knowing certainly whome to follow, nor what to belieue, vntill at the laſt, euen the wiſeſt of you being wearie of ſeeking, and deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate of finding that which they ſeeke, come to hold all opinions probable, which is in effect to belieue nothing.</p>
               <p>Good Syr, had you produced ſuch a Succeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſions of Nations, ſuch Myracles and Cenſures, in the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21663:16"/>
defence of your Church, as that Booke hath ſhewed in confirmation of theirs, all zealous Proteſtants had been bound to haue fallen at your feete, and to haue honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red you for euer. But now, on the other ſide, againſt ſuch weighty and maſſie matters, ſuch cleare and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincing proofes as theſe, not being able to giue in eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſo much as one Profeſſor in euery Age, nor in any Age the conuerſion of any Nation, or the teſtimony of any Myracle, or the Cenſure of any one Father in fauour of your Religion; who ſeeth not, that inſteed of reaſon there is nothing but paſſion on your part; and certainly for the honour of your cauſe, it were better to hold your peace, then reply ſo weakely in a matter of ſuch impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
               <p>For beſides all that hath beene ſayd againſt many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther moſt expreſſe Sentences of the Auncient Fathers, in thoſe very poynts which you haue choſen to touch; you haue only produced a few dribling Authorities, as it were on the Bye, ſome falſely tranſlated, and ſome falſely ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ſome in reſpect of other expreſſe words agaynſt you, plainely falſified; that, not to accuſe you of a bad Conſcience, though you make profeſſion to be much verſed in the Fathers, yet the Reader muſt needes think, you neuer ſaw, or read ſo much as thoſe few places which your ſelfe haue cited, but only tooke them by retaile fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> others. And howſoeuer, though they were admitted and taken as you giue them vp; yet in my poore opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, they eyther touch not your Aduerſaries at all, or being a little conſidered, make rather with them, then againſt them. Which ſheweth great want of iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in you: and I verily thinke, if you will be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to examine them with me, I ſhall make you ſee it. Wherefore as in the former Section, ſoe that you may know in this alſo, how far you are chargable, I giue you the ſumme of your accompt in this manner. <hi>The Doctrine of that Church which was condemned by the Fathers
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21663:17"/>
of the firſt fiue hundred yeares, was condemned by Chriſt and his Apostles. But the Doctrine of the Protestant Church, was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Fathers of the firſt</hi> 500. <hi>yeares, as the moſt and beſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Proteſtants themſelues haue alſo confeſſed.</hi> Ergo, <hi>the Doctrine of the Protestant Church, was likewiſe condemned by Chriſt and his Apoſtles.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Section V.</hi> Myracles defended to be a ſufficient Teſtimony of Truth, and the Doctrine of the Fathers therein declared.</head>
               <p>WHerefore to begin, as you doe, with Myra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, moſt certaine it is, that no true Myra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle can be wrought, but only by him, <hi>Qui facit mirabilia magna ſolus;</hi> and therefore whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer any true Myracle is ſhewed, or ſufficiently teſtified vnto vs, in confirmation of any point of Doctrine; it is an euident proofe of the truth thereof. For a Myracle in that caſe, is the Teſtimony of God, who ſpeaketh by workes, as men by wordes (ſayth S. <hi>Aug. Epiſt.</hi> 49. <hi>quaeſt.</hi> 6.) and is the ſubſcription (as it were) of his hand and ſeale vnto it. And certainly if Myracles were no ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t proofes of true Doctrine, they would neuer haue beene called, <hi>Signes and Teſtimonyes in holy Scripture.</hi> God would not haue giuen Moyſes power of working Myracles. <hi>Exod.</hi> 4. <hi>That the People of Iſrael might belieue he had appeared vnto him.</hi> Our Sauiour would not haue ſayd, the Iewes had not ſinned in not receauing him, <hi>if he had not done thoſe workes which no man els had done before him. Ioan.</hi> 15. And in vayne ſhould he haue promiſed, that <hi>Signes should follow thoſe that belieued,</hi> and haue <hi>cooperated</hi> and <hi>confirmed</hi> the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Apoſtles by them. Neyther could he in Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21663:17"/>
haue commaunded the world vpon paine of damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to belieue a thing ſo incredible, as that Chriſt being Crucified, was riſen againe in his owne fleſh, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended into Heauen, if many other Myracles which the Apoſtles wrought in confirmation therof, had not made it euidently credible, as S. <hi>Auſten</hi> diſputeth in his booke <hi>de Ciuit. Dei lib.</hi> 22. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. and in the former <hi>Epist.</hi> 49. <hi>quaeſt.</hi> 6. albeit he well obſerued, that this kind of proofe was euer lowdly and extremely laught at, by the wicked Pagans: yet moſt true it is, which there he alſo affirmeth, that we ſhould not belieue, Chriſt to be riſen againe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Dead, if the Fayth of Chriſtians did feare in this point of Myracles, the laughter of Pagans.</p>
               <p>Wherefore to anſwere thoſe places of the Fathers which you obiect, not only agaynſt ſo many of their owne Teſtimonies alleaged by your Aduerſary, but alſo againſt Scripture, and againſt Chriſtian beliefe it ſelfe, grounded vpon Myracles as hath beene noted; you muſt further vnderſtand, that the world hauing beene once perſwaded by myraculous operations and workes of wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to belieue the Doctrine of the Apoſtles with this fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me promiſe, that it ſhould alwayes remaine with them and their Succeſſors, the viſible Paſtors of the Catholike Church, vniuerſally ſpread ouer all the world; it ought not to belieue any other Doctrine, or any other Myra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles pretended to be done in oppoſition to that Doctrine which by continuall Tradition hath beene receaued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them. For as there can be no after-word of God, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that which was firſt preached; ſoe there can be no latter Myracles contrary to the teſtimony of thoſe, by which the world firſt belieued; but rather as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, If an Angell from Heauen ſhould preach otherwiſe then we haue receaued, we ſhould hold him accurſed. This made <hi>Tertullian</hi> in the Booke you cite <hi>de Praeſc. cap.</hi> 44. to proteſt againſt all Myracles ſuppoſed to be done againſt the Tradition of the Church; whereof S. <hi>Augustine</hi> in his
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21663:18"/>
Booke <hi>de vnit. Eccleſ.</hi> obiected by you, giueth the reaſon yet more plainly, ſhewing that the Catholike amplitude or vniuerſality of the Church, by conuerſions of Nations in all Ages, doth more euidently proue it to be the true Church of Chriſt, then any other worke which is done therein; for it is more manifeſt to ſenſe and human rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that the cleare Propheſies of the true Church in holy Scripture are fullfilled and accompliſhed only in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church, which accordingly in all Ages doth vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly ſpread it ſelfe ouer all the world, then it can poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly appeare, that any worke of admiration is truly a My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle ſurpaſſing the force of Nature, or power of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell; whereof it followeth, that the true Church is more manifeſtly knowne by the accompliſhment of thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, then by the wondrous effects of any Myracles; and that Myracles doe not ſoe well, and cleerly proue any Church to be Catholike, as the Church being viſibly Catholike, doth manifeſt thoſe Myracles to be true, which are approued by it.</p>
               <p>Whereof it followeth againe, that all Myracles which are done againſt it, or agaynſt the vnity thereof, are as firmely and conſtantly to be reiected. Which is it that he alſo teacheth, <hi>lib.</hi> 13. <hi>cont. Faust. cap.</hi> 5. and <hi>Tract.</hi> 13. <hi>in Ioan.</hi> and <hi>lib.</hi> 22. <hi>de Ciuitat. Dei, cap.</hi> 8. obiected by you. And heere by the way I beſeech you to note, how much Saint <hi>Anſten</hi> eſteemeth the former Argument of the conuerſions of Nations in all Ages, according to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes therof in holy Scripture, which he maketh ſuch an euident marke, and ſuch an infallible proofe of the true Church, that he preferreth it before Myracles. And for the ſame cauſe, <hi>lib.</hi> 22. <hi>de Ciuit. Dei, cap.</hi> 8. he ſpareth not to ſay: <hi>That he who ſeeketh to be confirmed by Wonders now, is himſelfe to be wondred at, in refuſing to belieue, that which all the world</hi> (or the viſible Church through the world) <hi>belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth.</hi> Which your ſelfe alſo hauing obſerued, you may wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der at your ſelf, both in refuſing to belieue, what you
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21663:18"/>
know the viſible Catholike Church, for a thouſand yeares, through the world, belieued, and (wherin I alſo wonder my ſelfe) at your not obſeruing, that S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> doth wonder at you in that very place, wherein you ſuppoſe he agreed with you, as by and by I ſhall make it appeare.</p>
               <p>Adde in the meane tyme to that which hath beene ſayd, that the Myracles whereunto the holy Fathers, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged by you, forbid vs to giue credit, as vnto Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments not ſufficient to proue the Truth of Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, were eyther Myracles in apparence only, and ſuch wherewith Heretikes <hi>might eaſily be deceaued, or ſo deceaue,</hi> as S. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine</hi> ſpeaketh in the former place vpon <hi>Ioan:</hi> not ſuch as might reaſonably induce any prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t man to belieue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. As Dreames, and Viſions, and exauditions of Prayers, like vnto thoſe of the Donatiſts, againſt whome wrote <hi>Saint Augustine lib. de Vnit. Eccl. cap.</hi> 16. Or ſuch as were Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the Iuſtice and mercy of God in generall, and not of Doctrine in particuler, as were thoſe whereof S. <hi>Hierome</hi> ſpeaketh: Or finally ſuch as being wrought by wicked men, exceeded not the power of the Diuell, as S. <hi>Augustine</hi> obſerueth, <hi>lib.</hi> 20. <hi>de Ciuit. Dei cap.</hi> 19. <hi>&amp; Tract.</hi> 13. <hi>in Ioan.</hi> Or were not ſufficiently teſtified, but rather ſayd then proued, which <hi>Tertullian lib. de Praeſer.</hi> derideth and ſayth, that the power of Heretiks was nothing like, but rather contrary, to the power of the Apoſtles; for their vertue was not to rayſe the Dead, but rather to kill the liuing, literally fullfilled in Caluin, <hi>Bolſec. in vita Caluini,</hi> who pretending by his prayer to rayſe a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfaite dead man, being then truly aliue, was thought to be the cauſe, that he was inſtantly ſlaine, eyther by God, or the Diuell. In the ſame ſenſe alſo <hi>Epiph. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de haer. cap.</hi> 30. vrgeth <hi>Ebion,</hi> to rayſe ſome dead man &amp;c. aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring himſelfe that he could not doe any true Myracle, <hi>by meanes of his falſe Faith, yea though he called vpon the name of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21663:19"/>
Christ.</hi> Not ſo the Myracles alleaged by your Aduerſary, which hauing beene wrought and belieued, and moſt authentically teſtified by ſoe many moſt holy, moſt prudent, and learned Witneſſes, in confirmation of that Doctrine which is profeſſed againſt you, need no more to feare the laughter of Proteſtants, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Myracles of former tymes, as <hi>S. Auſten</hi> ſaith, had cauſe to feare the laughter of Pagans. And ſuch as belieue them not, may iuſtly feare to be condemned as Pagans, for belieuing nothing. To deny therefore this Doctrine of Myracles, ſeemeth noe leſſe impious, then to deny Chriſtianity it ſelfe: and to affirme that myracles haue ceaſed ſithence the tyme of the Apoſtles, were noe leſſe vnreaſonable, then to reiect all humane Teſtimonies, and in particuler the Authority of <hi>S. Augustine</hi> himſefe, in thoſe very places obiected by you.</p>
               <p>For in that very place of <hi>S. Aug. de Ciuit. Dei, lib.</hi> 22. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. which you alleage againſt Myracles, <hi>That they were neceſſary before the world belieued, to induce it to belieue:</hi> And, <hi>That he that ſeeketh to be confirmed by wonders now, is himſelfe to be wondred at, in refuſing to belieue that which all the world</hi> (or the viſible Catholike Church through the world) <hi>belieueth:</hi> which being well conſidered, maketh little for you. In that very place (I ſay) you could not chooſe but read theſe other words directly againſt you; <hi>That now alſo Myracles are wrought in his Name, eyther by his Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or by the prayers, and memories of his Saints;</hi> togeather with the relation of many Myracles done in his owne tyme, and of thoſe in particuler wrought by the Reliques of S. <hi>Stephen,</hi> which though not neceſſary after the World had once belieued, as <hi>S. Austen</hi> there diſputeth; yet God in his mercy hath euer ſhewed them in all Ages, as well to confound the obſtinate that would not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue the viſible vniuerſall Church, as alſo to confirme thoſe in their Fayth, that already belieued. In this place
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21663:19"/>
therefore you haue plainely falſified the ſenſe of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, eyther very fraudulently, or very ignorantly, chooſe you whether.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Section VI.</hi> Merits of VVorkes defended, according to the Doctrine of the Fathers: and Syr Humphry anſwered.</head>
               <p>IN the next place againſt the Merit of Workes, you obiect many places of the Fathers, but none to the purpoſe. You know full well, that the Catholikes diſtinguiſh betweene works that goe before Faith, &amp; workes that follow. Workes going before Faith, and proceeding only from the light of Nature, or from the knowledge of the law of Moyſes (called therefore by <hi>S. Paul Rom.</hi> 3. <hi>The workes of the Law</hi>) your Aduerſaries doe all hold, neyther to ſaue, nor to be needfull to ſaluatio; according whereunto S. <hi>Paule</hi> alſo ſaith; <hi>That a Man is iuſtified by Faith, without the workes of the Law.</hi> But that workes following a liuely Faith, formed with Charity, and proceeding from it, doe iuſtifie, and are needfull to ſaluation, your Aduerſary proueth not only by expreſſe Scripture, <hi>Iames cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Yee ſee then how that of workes a man is iuſtified, and not of Faith only:</hi> But alſo by the lyke Teſtimonies of all the holy Fathers, noting and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning the contrary opinion of the Proteſtants as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall, in Symon Magus, in the Gnoſtickes, and in <hi>Euno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mius,</hi> as hath beene ſhewed. And further he alleadgeth S. <hi>Aug. de fide</hi> &amp; <hi>oper. cap.</hi> 14. teſtifiyng of the Apoſtles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, that becauſe this opinion of Faith only, ſprung vp in thoſe dayes, by peruerting the words of S. <hi>Paules Epistle</hi> before related, the <hi>Epistles</hi> of <hi>S. Peter, S. Iohn,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:21663:20"/>
S. Iames,</hi> and <hi>S. Iude,</hi> were principally written, <hi>vt vehemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter astruant,</hi> vehemently to vrge, and conteſt that Fayth without workes doth profit nothing. Agaynſt all which manifeſt proofes, you bring only ſome Authorityes of the Fathers, ſhewing that <hi>our owne workes and righteouſnes</hi> (as <hi>Baſil. hom. de Humil.) or workes of the Law,</hi> going before Fayth (as S. <hi>Chryſoſ.</hi> with S. <hi>Paul. Hom.</hi> 7. <hi>in</hi> 3. <hi>ad Rom.</hi>) and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Sinne pardoned (as S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi>) and forgiuen (as <hi>Theodoret comment.</hi> 2. S. <hi>Bernard in Cant. Ser.</hi> 22.) doe not iuſtifie, but <hi>only Fayth</hi> without them; which is nothing to the purpoſe becauſe therein your Aduerſary agreeth with you. But you bring not a word to proue that workes following Faith doe not iuſtify, nor are needfull to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation; which opinion of yours, your Aduerſary hath ſhewed to haue beene often tymes condemned by the Apoſtles themſelues, &amp; by the Auncient Fathers in other Heretikes that haue gone before you.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Section VII.</hi> Free-will defended: and Syr Humphry anſwered.</head>
               <p>IN the Controuerſy of Free-will, you ſeeme firſt to ſuppoſe your Aduerſaries belieue, that Man hath Free-will to performe ſupernaturall actes and workes of Pietie without Grace, and then you proceed to diſpute againſt them. How can you imagine, they are ſo abſurd as to thinke by the power of Nature alone to doe that which they the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeues confeſſe to be aboue the power of Nature, wherin there appeareth not only a great deale of paſſion in you, (which hanges lyke to a Cloud bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weene the Eye of your minde, and the light of truth) but alſo (as it ſeemeth) great want of conſcience.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:21663:20"/>For you know they hold, that without grace, it is impoſſible eyther to belieue, or to do any other acte which may auayle, or ſo much as diſpoſe to Saluation. This alſo you know to be the Doctrine of <hi>Bellarmine</hi> eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where in that whole Booke, out of which you ſeeme to cite his words in a contrary ſenſe: and the words that immediatly follow in the very place you cite, do plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhew, that againſt your Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience you falſify his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. His words are theſe: <hi>A Man before all grace hath Free-will, not only to naturall and morall workes, but alſo to workes of piety and ſupernaturall,</hi> as you faythfully cite them: but then it followeth, <hi>Thus S. Augustine teacheth, l. de Spiritu &amp; litera, cap.</hi> 33. where he ſayth; <hi>That Free-will is a naturall and mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle power, which may be inclined to fayth, and infidelity.</hi> Thus Bellarmine; whereby it is manifeſt his meaning to be, that by Grace, Free-will is not made, or giuen vnto vs, but that we haue the power thereof by Nature, which afterward by Grace is inclyned and ſtrengthned to doe thoſe things which by the force of Nature, without Grace, we are not able ſo much, as to will, or to thinke, much leſſe to performe or perfect; according whereunto, in the ſame place, he citeth alſo <hi>S. August. de Praedest. Sanctorum, cap.</hi> 5. teaching, that the <hi>Poſse, or power to haue Fayth and Charity, is in man by Nature.</hi> And in the ſame Booke, <hi>cap.</hi> 11. he alleageth <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> againe <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 49. <hi>quaest.</hi> 2. to the ſame purpoſe, ſaying: <hi>Free-will is not taken away, becauſe it is holpen</hi> (by Grace;) <hi>but becauſe it is holpen, therefore it is not taken away.</hi> If it be giuen by Nature, and not taken away by Grace, moſt certaine it is, that ſtill we haue it. In this ſenſe therefore, your Aduerſaries not only affirming, that we haue Freewill by Nature, but alſo teaching that it is ſo excited and ſtrengthned by Grace, as we cannot ſo much as thinke, much leſſe accompliſh or performe any ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall acte without it; they would eaſily graunt with <hi>S. Baſil, con. de Hum.</hi> that we owe all, euen that we liue, <hi>to the Grace and gift of God;</hi> but that you falſely tranſlate it.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:21663:21"/>
They graunt with <hi>S. Bernard de Gratia &amp; lib. Arbit. That to will Good, is a gift of Grace.</hi> And with S. <hi>Auguſtine. That it is God, who maketh that we worke, by adding to our will moſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacious strength. That vnleſſe he make vs willing, and then worke with vs, we shall neuer bring to paſse any good worke.</hi> And againe with S. <hi>Auguſtine de correp. &amp; grat. cap.</hi> 1. <hi>That though we haue Free-will to doe good, yet none can be free in will and acte to do it, that is to ſay, perfectly, or in actu ſecundo,</hi> as the Scholmen ſpeake, <hi>vnleſſe he be freed by the grace of God.</hi> And againe: <hi>That all is to be giuen to God, not the firſt part vnto our ſelues, &amp; the rest vnto God,</hi> as the Pelagians did, againſt whome S. <hi>Augustine</hi> diſputeth, but all vnto God, and vnto our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues nothing that is not of God. And againe, <hi>That without God we cannot prepare our owne harts.</hi> And againe, <hi>That Gods grace doth not forme, but reforme our Nature,</hi> by giuing it the grace wherewith it was firſt formed. And finally, <hi>Ench. ad Laurent. cap.</hi> 32. <hi>That of his mercy he prepareth our will to be holpen, and helpeth it being prepared.</hi> Whereby (condemning your Aduerſaries as you doe, and yet eyther not knowing what they hold, or maliciouſly miſtaking their meaning) you may ſee at the laſt, that with a great deale of labour, for want of a little learning, if not for want of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, you haue rather confirmed, then cenſured their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
               <p>But now that we haue no Free-will to any act at all, in ſuch manner, as it lyeth not in our power to doe it, or not to doe it; and that all things are done neceſſarily, though willingly, becauſe all things are done by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euitable decree of God, being the point you ſhould haue proued; none of the Fathers you alleadge, eyther thought or ſayd, but haue condemned it for Hereſie and Error in Simon Magus, and in the Manichees: yea, and becauſe it followeth from hence, that God is the Author of ſinne, euen for more then Hereſie, in Florinus, <hi>vt refert Euſeb. l.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 20. Heere againe I muſt friendly admoniſh you, that negligently or ignorantly being deceaued by others,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:21663:21"/>
you haue falſely quoted S. <hi>Auguſtine de grat. &amp; lib. Arbit. c.</hi> 16. <hi>Except God firſt make vs willing &amp;c.</hi> And againe, <hi>de Nat. &amp; Grat. cap.</hi> 35. <hi>Why doe we preſume ſo much &amp;c.</hi> which wordes with the reſt that follow, are not to be found in thoſe place: neyther if they were, would they make any thing for you, as your ſelfe will iudge by that which hath beene ſayd. And againe you alleage <hi>S. Auguſtine lib.</hi> 13. <hi>de bono perſeuer. cap.</hi> 6. there being but one ſingle Booke of that Argument, and in that Chapter, thoſe wordes are not found which you haue there alleaged. You cite him alſo, <hi>cont. duas Epist. Pelag. lib.</hi> 2. which ſecond Booke hauing 10. Chapters, you quote no Chapter. Will your Reader impute ſo many imperfect and falſe quotations only to the error of your pen, and not rather to your ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, or want of due peruſall?</p>
               <p>But how will you defend your ſelfe, in alleaging theſe other words out of <hi>S. Auſten: It is certaine that we worke, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we do ſo, but it is he that giueth vs this working power, by adding vnto our will, moſt effectuall ſtrength;</hi> as if he had ſayd, <hi>I will make you worke.</hi> Whereby you will make your Reader belieue, that according vnto <hi>S. Auſten</hi> we haue no power of Free-will by Nature, but that God giueth it, by adding his Grace; which is not ſo: for <hi>S. Austen</hi> doth not ſay, It is he that giueth vs this working power, by adding ſtrength to our will as you alleage, but that, <hi>He maketh vs to worke, by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſtrength to our will</hi> (or which is all one) <hi>to the power of our will;</hi> which therfore proueth, that we haue power of will by Nature, though not ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly able to do any ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall act, before he adde the ſtrength of his Grace vnto it. Againe you finde not in S. <hi>Augustine</hi> theſe other words of yours: <hi>as if he ſayd, I will make you worke;</hi> but they are by you fraudule<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly foiſted in, to cut off, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceale the words that follow. For wheras Pelagius, to proue that we are able by Nature without Grace to keepe the Commaundements obiected out of <hi>Eccleſiasticus: Si volueris, ſeruabis mandata,</hi> if thou wilt, thou ſhalt keep the Commaundements: <hi>S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> anſwereth, he knew as well as Pelagius, that they
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:21663:22"/>
that will, ſhall be able to keep them, yet not by Nature as he would haue it, but by Grace, holding it for certaine, that we are able to keepe them, but ſo as that God is he who worketh in vs both to will and to performe them. The words of S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> are theſe that follow: <hi>It is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that we will when we worke, but it is he that maketh vs to will, of whome it is ſayd; It is God that worketh in vs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o will; It is certaine that we worke when we worke, but he maketh that we may be able to worke, giuing most efficacious ſtrength vnto our will, who ſayd; I will make them walke in my Iuſtifications, and to keepe my Iudgments, and to doe them.</hi> Which laſt wordes you partly changed, and partly omitted, to conceale the Doctrine of <hi>S. Auguſtine,</hi> and his proofes out of Scripture, ſhewing that by Grace we are able to keepe the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, which the Proteſtants haue euer held impoſſible. Laſtly as if you meant not to be diſcouered, you cite the former words out of his Booke. <hi>De bono perſeuer. lib.</hi> 13. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. which are only to be found in <hi>De Grat. &amp; lib. Arbit. cap.</hi> 16. Let this be ignorance in you, which in another were plaine forgery.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Section VIII. S.</hi> Cyprian falſly alleaged by Syr Humphry, againſt the Reall Preſence.</head>
               <p>FInally concerning the B. Sacraments, you only taxe one Authority cited by your Aduerſary out of S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> in his Sermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Of the ſupper of our Lord,</hi> and alleadge another againſt it out of the ſame Author, in his Sermon <hi>Of the Vnction of Chriſme,</hi> which Chriſme (as it is there recorded) was vſually made at that tyme vpon holy Thurſday of Oyle and Balſamum (as now alſo it is accuſtomed) for the vſe of the Church in Baptiſme, and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:21663:22"/>
other Sacraments: So hard it is for one of you to alleage any thing out of the Fathers, which one way or other doth not make againſt you. The words alleaged by your Aduerſary are theſe: <hi>The Bread which our Lord gaue to his Diſciples, being changed not in shape, but in Nature, by the omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency of the Word, is made flesh.</hi> A place ſo playne for Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation, or change of ſubſtance in the Sacrament, that when I read it, it makes me bluſh at the bouldnes of thoſe Diuines who dare to auouch that Tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſubſtantiatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was neuer known before the Councell of Lateran. Now in this ſentence, <hi>(forgetting the beame in your owne eye) you ſeeke a mote in the eye of your Brother,</hi> accuſing him, becauſe to be vnderſtood, he tranſlated the word which ſignifieth Nature, to ſignify Subſtance, or Nature. If you were as good a Philoſopher, as you pretend to be a great Diuine, you could not be ignorant that theſe three wordes, <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Substance,</hi> and <hi>Eſſence,</hi> are all equiualente, ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame thing in diuers conſiderations; that which is called <hi>Nature</hi> in order to motion, is called <hi>Subſtance</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the Accidents, and <hi>Eſſence</hi> in reference to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition of it. And I pray you Syr, there being nothing in Bread but ſhape and ſubſtance, he who ſayth, <hi>That Bread being changed, not in shape, but in Nature, by the omnipotency of the Word, is made Flesh,</hi> what doth he affirme, but that it is changed in ſubſtance?</p>
               <p>Secondly, you accuſe him for alleaging thoſe words out of <hi>Cyprian,</hi> which Bellarmine himſelfe <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Euch. cap.</hi> 9. holdeth to be none of <hi>Cyprians;</hi> Wherein you muſt giue me leaue to tell you, that your ſelfe much more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue to be accuſed. For firſt, albeit Bellarmine doth ſay, he thinketh that Sermon <hi>de Coena Domini,</hi> not to be <hi>S. Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prians,</hi> yet he addeth immediatly in the ſame place, that it is, <hi>The Sermon of ſome auncient, moſt holy, and most learned Man, as the Aduerſaries</hi> (meaning Proteſtants) <hi>do confeſſe;</hi> which words (that you might with more ſhew eleuate, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyd the former Authority) were fraudulently concealed
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:21663:23"/>
by you. <hi>It is the worke of ſome learned Man of that Age,</hi> ſayth <hi>Eraſmus</hi> in his annotations vpon the workes of <hi>S. Cyprian, In tyme not much inferior to Cyprian,</hi> ſayth <hi>Fulke, in</hi> 1. <hi>Corinth. cap.</hi> 11. Wherefore doe we reuerence the Authority of <hi>S. Cyprian,</hi> but becauſe he was an Auncient, holy, and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Father? If therefore the Author of this Sermon, was a moſt holy and learned Man, as Bellarmine ſayth the Proteſtants themſelues confeſſe, and of the ſame Age with <hi>S. Cyprian,</hi> or in tyme not much inferior vnto him, as I haue ſhewed that the Proteſtants themſelues doe likewiſe witneſſe, why ſhould any Proteſtant reiect him?</p>
               <p>Beſides, though Bellarmine thinketh this Sermon to be none of <hi>Cyprians,</hi> yet many other <hi>Deuines of great name Cypriano tribuunt, doe iudge it to be the worke of S. Cyprian, as well for the likeneſſe of the ſtale, as for the dignity of the matter,</hi> ſayth <hi>Gaulortius</hi> a learned Proteſtant in his annotations thereupon. Why then may not your Aduerſarie follow heerein, the iudgment of many other great Deuines? In fine, your Aduerſary may alleage for himſelfe in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the teſtimony of <hi>S. Augustine cont Donat. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap</hi> 22. his words are theſe: <hi>From that Theefe to whome, not being baptized, it was ſayd, This day thou shalt be with me in Paradiſe;</hi> the ſame <hi>S. Cyprian tooke no ſleight document, that paſsion</hi> (or death, or Martyrdome) <hi>doth ſometyme ſupply the place of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</hi> According whereunto both in ſenſe and words in the ſame Sermon <hi>de Coena Domini,</hi> it is ſayd (and therefore according to <hi>S. Auguſtine,</hi> by <hi>S. Cyprian) That our Lord &amp;c. deferred not his benefit, but with the ſame ſpeedy Indulgence he gaue preſently aſwell a document, as alſo an example thereof, ſaying vnto the Theefe; This day thou shalt be with me in Paradiſe. He had his condemnation and punishment for robery, but his contritio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of hart changed his payne into Martyrdome, and his bloud into Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</hi> Why now may not your Aduerſary cite that Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon as Saint <hi>Cyprians,</hi> which Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> himſelfe ſo long a goe alleadged vnder the name of <hi>Cyprian?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, therefore heerein you deſerue both blame and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:21663:23"/>
ſhame, inſimulating your Aduerſary of fraud for miſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaging <hi>S. Cyprian</hi> by the teſtimony of Bellarmine, and fraudulently co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cealing thoſe words of Bellarmine in the ſame place; which euen the teſtimonyes of Proteſtants themſelues do ſhew the words alleaged by your Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary out of <hi>Cyprian,</hi> to be of no leſſe Authority, then the words of <hi>Cyprian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, you deſerue the more blame heerein, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you alleage agaynſt it another place out of S. <hi>Cypria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> which according to the opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Bellarmine in the ſame place, in the ſame Chapter, is none of <hi>Cyprians.</hi> And plaine it is, that the Sermon of <hi>the Supper of our Lord,</hi> alleaged by your Aduerſary, and the other of <hi>Chriſme</hi> alleadged by your ſelfe, are both the Sermons of the ſame Author; for the whole Booke contayning 12. Sermons, is intituled, <hi>Of the Cardinall workes of Christ,</hi> and dedicated to Pope <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius</hi> the Martyr, who liued in the tyme of <hi>Cyprian:</hi> And therefore he that denyeth the one, hath no reaſon to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme the other to be the worke of <hi>Cyprian.</hi> How then out of the ſame mouth could you breath both hoat and cold? And how out of the ſame Bellarmine could you proue the Sermon alleadged by your Aduerſary to be none of <hi>Cyprians,</hi> and affirme agaynſt Bellarmine the other allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by your ſelfe, to be the worke of <hi>Cyprian?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, the like foule fraude co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted by you appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth yet more groſſely in the words which you cite out of the ſame Author, who when you take him to be with you, is <hi>Cyprian,</hi> but not <hi>Cyprian</hi> when he ſpeaketh againſt you. The words of the Author are theſe: <hi>Our Lord there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore at that Table wherein he made his last Feaſt to his A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ostles, with his owne hands, gaue Bread and Wine: but at the Croſſe he gaue his Body to be wounded by the hands of his Enemie; that ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere verity, and true ſincerity (being more ſecretly im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>inted in the Apoſtles) might expound to Nations, how the Wine and the Bread was Flesh and Blood: and after what manner t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cauſes agreed with their effects: That diuers shapes might: brought to one
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:21663:24"/>
Eſſence, and the things ſignifiyng, and the things ſignified, might be called (and knowne) by the ſame names.</hi> Thus <hi>S. Cyprian.</hi> But not thus Syr Hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phry, for hauing alleaged the words which ſeemed to make for him, <hi>he gaue Bread and Wine to his Apostles, but his Body to his Enemies,</hi> he chopt off with an &amp;c. the words following, <hi>That ſincere verity, and true ſincerity, (being more ſecretly imprinted in the Apostles) might expound to Nations, how the Wine and Bread was flesh and Blood:</hi> which as euery man may ſee, are expreſſely againſt him, and ſerue to expound the meaning of the Author in the reſt of that Sentence; which though otherwiſe beeing a little obſcure, yet being a little conſidered, may be thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained. Our Lord ſayd to his Apoſtles, <hi>This is my bodie, which shall be giuen for you,</hi> when at the table he gaue to them viſibly Bread and Wine, but at the Croſſe he viſibly gaue his owne Body; that his Apoſtles thereby might vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly ſee, he had giuen them inuiſibly his owne Body; becauſe he gaue them the ſame Body into their owne hands, which was giuen for them, into the hands of their Enemies. 1. <hi>That the ſincere verity, and true ſincerity heereof, being thus ſecretly imprinted in the harts of the Apoſtles, they might confidently expound to all Nations, how the Bread and Wine of that table, was truly and ſincerely Flesh and Blood. 2. How the cauſes agreed with their effects, &amp; the words of our Sauiour, which were the cauſes going before, agreed with their effects, both at the Table, and at the Croſse, that followed after.</hi> 3. <hi>How vnder diuers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hapes of Bread and Wine at the Table, was contained but one &amp; the ſame Eſsence, becauſe the ſame ſhapes remayning, the Natures of Bread and Wine, by the omnipotency of the Word, were chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> reduced into the Nature of his Body;</hi> as before you haue heard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut of his former ſermon. 4. <hi>How the thinges ſignifying (which were the shapes of Bread and Wine remayning) and the things ſignified (which were the Body and Blood of our Sauiour) came both to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> called by the ſame names, becauſe the one did ſignify, exhibit, and co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aine the other.</hi> By all which it appeareth (the Author hauing his right brought backe againe, and his
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:21663:24"/>
owne breath being reſtored againe vnto him, which you had thought to ſteale and ſmother) that he plainely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth the Bread and Wine to be Fleſh and Blood, and that the Nature of the one being changed into the Nature of the other, they are both reduced into one Eſſence; which is the ſame Doctrine, that your Aduerſary profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, and maintayneth againſt you.</p>
               <p>Your Aduerſaries affirme, the Bread to be made a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament and the Body of Chriſt, by the words of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration, for the which cauſe they not only adore it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they receaue it, but alſo they haue euer held, that it might be lawfully giuen to Infants, and that which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines thereof they are wonte to reſerue to be giuen afterward to the ſicke, or to others that come to receaue, as occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> requireth. You Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts affirme on the other ſide, that it beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth a Sacrament, and a Seale of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt vnto you, without any change in the thing, by the liuely Faith of the Receauers; and conſequently you giue it not to Infants, becauſe they cannot receaue it with that Faith which makes it a Sacrament: and that alſo which remaineth thereof, after the whole Action, you take to be no better then common Bread, and ſoe you vſe it. As cuſtome is the beſt interpreter of the law, ſo the practiſe of the Church is the beſt interpreter of her owne Doctrine. Wherefore to know what S. <hi>Cypria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> with the Church of God in the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Age after Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieued at that tyme, concerning this point of the B. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, there can be no ſurer way, then to examine what is practized in communicating the ſame to Infants, and in reſeruing of it, to be taken as need required. Which S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> in his ſermon <hi>De Lapſis,</hi> his owne vndoubted worke, hath not obſcurely recorded: for he relateth <hi>(Teſte meipſo) &amp; ſacrificantibus nobis; my ſelfe being witnes, and we our ſelues offering ſacrifice,</hi> that an Infant hauing beene fedde with a ſopp of wine before an Idoll, and being after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward brought to Church, was much tormented during
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:21663:25"/>
the tyme of the Sacrifice, and when it's turne came to receaue, it reſiſted ſo vehemently, that the Deacon was faine perforce to open it's mouth, <hi>and to power in ſomewhat of the Sacrament that was in the Chalice;</hi> but (ſayth <hi>S. Cypria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) The drinke ſanctified into the Bloud of Christ, brake out of her pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted bowels &amp;c.</hi> In which Sermon he likewiſe teſtifieth: <hi>That a certaine Woman when she would with vnworthy hands haue opened her coffer, wherein was reſerued the Holy Thing of our Lord, there ſprung vp fire from thence, wherewith she was ſo ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, that she durst not touch it.</hi> And, <hi>That another defiled Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon preſuming to receaue with others, could not eate, nor touch the Holy Thing of God, for in his opened hands (inſteed thereof) he found Ashes. By Document whereof</hi> (ſayth <hi>S. Cyprian) it is shewed, that the Lord doth depart when he is denyed.</hi> By which Documents of reſeruing the <hi>Eucharist,</hi> and giuing it to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, they (who will not be obſtinate) may alſo learne out of <hi>S. Cyprian,</hi> that the <hi>Eucharist</hi> after the words of Conſecration, was belieued to be really the Body of Chriſt, and not figuratiuely by Fayth only, to him that doth worthily ſo receaue it. Wherefore to conclude this Diſpute, concerning the Teſtimony of <hi>S. Cyprian</hi> for Tranſubſtantiation, and Reall Preſence, as it was falſe that your Doctors claymed him in the former Confere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ſo being plaine agaynſt them in this point, beſides many other of no leſſe importance, it was fondly done of you, to ſay they claymed him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:21663:25"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Section IX.</hi> S. Auguſtine falſly alleadged by Syr Humphry, againſt the Reall Preſence.</head>
               <p>FYnally againſt the Reall Preſence you obiect other places of the Fathers, affirming the Sacrament to be a figure of Chriſts body, which your Aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries deny not. For they define all Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts to be ſignes and figures, according whereunto they alſo holde, that as the Sacrament of the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> is a figure, in reſpect of the Shape or externall accidents therof, ſo it is the Body of Chriſt, in reſpect of the thing contained in them.</p>
               <p>But now that the <hi>Eucharist</hi> is only a figure, or that it is not the Body of Chriſt, which you ſhould haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued againſt them, or els you proue nothing, none of the places alleaged by you do ſhew; neyther is it poſſible in all the Fathers to find ſo much as one place, that doth ſufficiently proue it. While they in the meane tyme (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides many moſt expreſſe Scriptures, <hi>Matt.</hi> 26. <hi>Marc.</hi> 14. <hi>Luc.</hi> 22. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 6. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. confuting alſo your principall obeiction, that the Body of Chriſt cannot be in two places, <hi>Act.</hi> 9.5.22.8.23.11. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.8.) They, I ſay, on the other ſide produce ſo many ſuperabu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dant Authorities from the Fathers &amp; Councells in all Ages, conuincing the holy <hi>Eucharist</hi> to be the Body of Chriſt, that I muſt needs ſay, they haue diſcouered more bouldnes (if not impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency) the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> learning or conſcience, who eyther in bookes or in Pulpits haue pretended to ſhew, that the Fathers in this point are plainely againſt them. To make this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, it may ſuffice at this tyme, briefely to ſet down the beliefe only of thoſe Fathers in particuler, which your ſelfe in your papers haue produced for you, <hi>Tertullian,</hi> S. <hi>Auſten, S. Ambroſe,</hi> S. <hi>Hierome</hi> and <hi>Gelaſius,</hi> ſhewing, how
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:21663:26"/>
euidently they teach the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary Doctrine aſwell in their writing elſwhere, as in thoſe very places which your ſelfe haue cited. Firſt therefore let vs begin with <hi>Saint Augustine;</hi> who in his Workes making often mention of the Sacrament, giueth vs theſe particulers of his Doctrine therein; <q>That before the words of Conſecration, that which was offered is called Bread; but after the words of Chriſt haue beene pronounced, now it is not called Bread, but it is called the Body, <hi>Serm.</hi> 28. <hi>de verb. Domini.</hi> That if Children had neuer ſeene the likenes of thoſe thinges, but only when it is offered, and giuen in the Celebration of the Sacrament, and that it ſhould be tould vnto them with moſt graue Authority whoſe Body and Bloud it is, they would belieue nothing els, but that our Lord had neuer appeared to the eyes of Men, ſaue only in that likenes, <hi>lib.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>de Trin. cap.</hi> 10. That Childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were wont to receaue it, <hi>apud Beda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. in</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. Who haue not the mouth of Faith to receaue it. That it pleaſed the Holy Ghoſt, &amp; was vniuerſally obſerued that our Lords body enter into the mouth of a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before other meates, in the honor of ſo great a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 118. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. which muſt needes be meant of the mouth of the Body. <hi>That we receaue with our hart and mouth the Mediator of God and Man Ieſus Chriſt, Man giuing vs his Flesh to be eaten, and his Bloud to be drunke, although it ſeeme more horrible to eate Mans fleſh, then to kill it, and to drinke Mans bloud then to ſpill it, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cont. Aduerſaer. legi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> &amp; Prophet. That we doe not eate dead flesh dilaniated, and cut in peeces, as the Capharnaites vnderſtood it;</hi> for this indeed were horible, and would profit nothing; but we eate the fleſh of Chriſt, as it is liuing fleſh, <hi>vegetated with his Spirit,</hi> which is Chriſt himſelfe entirely as he is now in Heauen, <hi>Tract.</hi> 27. <hi>in Ioan. &amp;</hi> 63 That no man eateth that Fleſh, before he adore it, <hi>in Pſalm.</hi> 93. That the rich men of this World co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to the Table of Chriſt do receaue his Body and Bloud, which though they
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:21663:26"/>
adore, yet are not filled with it, becauſe they doe not imitate it, eating him that is poore, but contemning pouerty, <hi>Epist.</hi> 120. <hi>ad Honoratum.</hi> That the Apoſtles did eate the Bread which was their Lord, <hi>Panem Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num;</hi> though Iudas did eate but the Bread of our Lord, <hi>Panem Domini, Tract.</hi> 59. <hi>in Ioan.</hi>
                  </q> For our Sauiour was not truly his Lord, becauſe Iudas was not truly his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant; And if at the day of Iudgement he ſhould ſay, <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, Domine,</hi> our Lord would anſwere, I know thee not.</p>
               <p>Proteſtants may well ſay with Iudas, that they eate the Bread of our Lord, if our Lord did ordaine it to be a figure of his Body, but they cannot ſay with the Apoſtles, that they eate the Bread which is their Lord, becauſe they deny it to be their Lords Body. <q>That Iudas Iſcariot receaued <hi>That</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>which the faythfull know, the price of our Redemption, Epist.</hi> 162. <hi>ad Glor.</hi> That our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our did literally beare himſelfe in his owne hands whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he gaue it, <hi>Conc.</hi> 1. <hi>in Pſalm.</hi> 33. That Biſhops and Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biters in the Church of Chriſt, are properly Prieſts, <hi>de Ciuit Dei, lib.</hi> 20. <hi>cap.</hi> 10. Which doth infer, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly alſo there are Prieſts and Sacrifices, &amp; that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Prieſts doe properly offer Sacrifice vpon <hi>Altars.</hi> Wherefore making often mention of MASSE, <hi>Serm.</hi> 91. <hi>de Tempore, &amp; Serm.</hi> 251. he ſayth likewiſe, that our Sauiour changed the Sacrifice according to the order of <hi>Aaron,</hi> and did inſtitute a Sacrifice of his owne Body and Bloud, according to the order of Melchiſedech, <hi>in Pſalm.</hi> 32. <hi>&amp; in Pſalm.</hi> 39. <hi>&amp; lib.</hi> 17. <hi>de Ciuit, Dei, cap.</hi> 20. That he prayed God, to giue him contrition &amp; a fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of teares, when he aſſiſted at the holy Altar, to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer that marueilous &amp; heauenly Sacrifice, which Chriſt the immaculate Prieſt did inſtitute and commaund to be offered, <hi>in Manuali.</hi> That a Prieſt of his offered the Sacrifice of the Body of Chriſt in a houſe infeſted with wicked ſpirits, which was thereby freed, <hi>lib.</hi> 22. <hi>de Ciu. Dei, cap.</hi> 8. That he deſired all Prieſts (whome he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:21663:27"/>
his Bretheren, and his Maiſters) who ſhould read his Booke of Confeſſions, to remember his Mother at the <hi>Altar,</hi> where the alſo deſired to be remembred after her death, <hi>lib</hi> 9. <hi>Confeſſ. cap.</hi> 13. That it is not to be doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the dead are holpen thereby, becauſe the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall Church receauing it from the Fathers, obſerued that it ſhould be offered for thoſe, who departed this life in the communion of Chriſts Body, <hi>Serm.</hi> 32. <hi>de verbis Apostoli.</hi> He reckoneth it amongſt the Hereſies of <hi>Aerius,</hi> that he denyed Oblations and Prayers for the Dead, <hi>Haer.</hi> 53.</q> Could any Catholike at this day, or Bellarmine himſelfe if he were now aliue, more fully declare his owne Doctrine in this point of the <hi>Reall Preſence,</hi> and of the Sacrifice of the Maſſe; then doth <hi>S. Augustine</hi> againſt you? though in other things you may retaine ſome dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties, yet in this me thinkes you ſhould freely acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that you are wholy conuinced.</p>
               <p>Finally, vpon <hi>Leuiticus, quaest.</hi> 57. in the very place which your ſelfe haue cited, where there is nothing that may found for you, but only that the figure is ſometymes ſayd to be the thing figured, <q>(which as I take, it is only in thoſe caſes, where it is knowne and preſuppoſed to be a figure) he demaundeth why the people ſhould be ſo much forbidden from the Bloud of the Sacrifice of the old Law, when as none were forbidden to take for their nouriſhment, the Bloud of this one Sacrifice, which was ſignified by all the former; but all that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired life, were rather exhorted to drinke it.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Now therefore heereupon, might not your Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries deeply charge you, that you had egregiouſly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed <hi>S. Augustine,</hi> and plainely peruerted his meaning?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:21663:27"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Section X. S.</hi> Ambroſe falſly alleaged by Syr Humphry, againſt the Reall Preſence.</head>
               <p>LEt vs now come to S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> who conuerted <hi>S. Auguſtine,</hi> that we may ſee how the Maiſter &amp; the Scholler agree togeather; he maketh mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the MASSE, and that himſelfe ſayd MASSE, <hi>Epiſt. ad Sororem Marcellinam.</hi> He repeateth a great part of the <hi>Canon</hi> of the MASSE, which is now vſed: <hi>We offer vnto thee this immaculate Host; this reaſonable Host; this vnbloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Hoſt; this holy Bread, and Cup of life euerlaſting &amp;c. And we pray thee to receaue this Oblation as thou didſt vouchſafe to receaue the gifts of thy ſeruant Abel the iust, and the Sacrifice of our great Father Abraham, and that which the high Priest Melchiſedech did offer vnto thee, lib.</hi> 4. <hi>de Sacramentis, cap.</hi> 6. He ſayth: <hi>We daily adore the Flesh of Christ in the Mysteries</hi> (that is to ſay, in the MASSE, or Sacrifice) <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de Spirit. Sanct. cap.</hi> 12. He maketh his prayer vnto that Bread, <hi>to heale his infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to come into his hart, to clenſe both his flesh and his ſpirit from all that defileth,</hi> in his prayer preparatory before <hi>Maſse.</hi> And in his Booke <hi>De Mysterijs init. cap.</hi> 9. he obiecteth in this manner; <hi>Perchance thou wilt ſay, I ſee another thing, how doſt thou affirme vnto me, that I receaue the Body of Christ?</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto he anſwereth: <hi>How many Examples haue we to proue it, not to be that which Nature hath formed, but that which Benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction hath conſecrated: And that Benediction is of greater power then Nature, becauſe by it, euen Nature it ſelfe, is changed?</hi> And then declaring many Myracles wrought by <hi>Moyſes, Helias,</hi> and <hi>Helizaeus,</hi> he concludeth: <hi>If human benediction were able to change Nature, what shall we ſay of Diuine Conſecration? If the ſpeach of Helias was able to bring Fyre from the Heauens; Shall not the ſpeach of Chriſt be able to change the formes of the Elements?
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:21663:28"/>
If the word of Christ were able to make of nothing that which was not, can it not change the things that are, into that which they were not? For it is no leſse matter to giue new Natures vnto things, then to change their Natures.</hi> And a little after he ſayth: <hi>It is manifeſt that a Virgin brought forth agaynst the ordinary courſe of Nature, and the Body which we</hi> (Prieſts DOE MAKE) <hi>is of the Virgin: What dost thou require the order of Nature</hi> (to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued) <hi>in the Body of Christ, who was borne of a Virgin againſt the order of Nature?</hi> Could the Doctrine of Tranſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, or change of Nature in the Sacrament, be more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouched, or better proued by any moderne Papiſt? Who likewiſe <hi>lib.</hi> 6. <hi>de Sacram. cap.</hi> 1. thinketh it no blaſphemy to ſay, as he doth, <hi>That as our Lord Ieſus Christ is the true So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of God, not as man by grace</hi> (or by Fayth) <hi>but as the Sonne of the ſubſtance of his Father: ſo</hi> (as he himſelfe hath ſayd) <hi>it is true Flesh which we receaue;</hi> That is to ſay, not by grace, or by Fayth only, but in Truth, and in Subſtance.</p>
               <p>Finally in the place which you cite for your ſelfe, <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. <hi>de Sacram.</hi> (where there is nothing to be found in your fauour) he hath theſe expreſſe words. <hi>Therefore before Conſecration, it is Bread; but after the words of Chriſt come to it, it is the Body of Christ. And before the words of Christ, it is a Cup full of Wine and Water; when the words of Chriſt haue wrought, then it is made the Bloud which redeemed the People. To conclude, our Lord Ieſus teſtifieth vnto vs, that we receaue his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Bloud; Ought we to doubt of his Fayth and Teſtimony?</hi> Heere if I had concealed the name of S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> would not the Reader thinke, the man had liued in our tyme, that wrore ſo forcibly and vehemently agaynſt you?</p>
               <p>Finally, in the former Chapter of the ſame Booke he ſaith againe: <hi>The bread, is bread before the words of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, but after the words of Conſecration, of Bread is made the flesh of Chriſt.</hi> And againe in the ſame little Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as if by often repeating the ſame thing he meant to vexe or confound euery obſtinate Proteſtant that ſhould reade it, he ſaith: <hi>Therefore, that I may anſwere thee; It
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:21663:28"/>
was not the Body of Chriſt before Conſecration, but after Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration,</hi> I <hi>ſay vnto thee, it is the Body of Chriſt.</hi> And agayne a little after, repeating the ſame againe, as if he had now conuinced his Readers, he concludeth: <hi>You haue therefore learned; that our Bread is made the Body of Chriſt, and that Wine &amp; Water is put into the Chalice, but is made Bloud by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration of the heauenly Word: But it may be thou wilt ſay, I ſee not the forme of Bloud. But it hath the likeneſſe; for as thou haſt receaued the likeneſſe of death, ſo thou drinkest alſo the likeneſſe of Bloud, and not the viſible forme of Bloud, that there might be noe horror of Bloud; and yet the price of our Redemption, which is the Bloud of Christ, might worke in vs. Thou hast learned therefore, that thou receaueſt the Body of Christ.</hi> Which you alſo might haue learned, if you had read him your ſelfe, and not tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted others that read him for no other purpoſe, but only to wreſt his words againſt his meaning.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Section XI.</hi> S. Hierome falſly alleaged, by Syr Humphry, agaynſt the Reall Preſence.</head>
               <p>NOW come we to S. <hi>Hierome,</hi> who thinketh it noe blaſphemy to ſay <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 1. <hi>ad Heliod. That Priests with their ſacred Mouthes doe make the Body of Chriſt. And, Epiſt. ad Euag. That his Body and Bloud is made at their prayer.</hi> And, <hi>in cap.</hi> 25. <hi>Matth.</hi> writeth as <hi>fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth: After the typicall Paſsouer was ended &amp;c. he taketh Bread and paſſeth ouer to the Sacrament of the true Paſſouer, that as Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedech the Priest of the moſt high God had done, offering Bread and Wine to prefigure him; he alſo might repreſent the truth of his Body and Bloud.</hi> That is to ſay, as Melchiſedech offered Bread and Wine to prefigure him; ſo he alſo taking Bread and wine, offered the truth of his Body and Bloud to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:21663:29"/>
the figure. According wherunto, in <hi>Pſ.</hi> 190. ſpeaking to our Sauiour he ſaith: <hi>As Melchiſedech offereth Bread and Wine; ſoe thou alſo offereſt thy Body and Bloud, the true Bread and the true Wine.</hi> In that ſenſe, true Bread, as in <hi>Epist. ad He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibiam, quaeſt.</hi> 2. he ſaith, that <hi>Moyſes gaue noe true Bread;</hi> And as our Sauiour ſayd, <hi>Ioan.</hi> 6. <hi>That his Father gaue them true Bread from heauen.</hi> Where alſo S. <hi>Hierome</hi> hath theſe words: <hi>Let vs heare the Bread which our Lord brake, to be the Body of our Lord and Sauiour.</hi> And he adeth a little after. <hi>He ſate at the Banquet, and was himſelfe the Banquet; he the eater, and be that was eaten.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Finally, <hi>lib. cont. Vigil. cap.</hi> 3. he reprehendeth <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilantius,</hi> for ſpeaking againſt Reliques in this manner; <hi>Therefore</hi> (according to thy ſpeach) <hi>the Bishop of Rome doth ill, who vpon the Bones of Peter and Paul (which we call venerable, but thou eſteemeſt moſt vile duſt) doth offer Sacrifices to God, and maketh their To<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bes to be the Altars of Chriſt.</hi> According wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto <hi>in Prouerb.</hi> 11. he alſo ſaith; <hi>That after this life, ſmall ſinnes may be taken away, by paine, by prayers, and almes of others, and by celebrations of MASSE.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly in his Booke againſt <hi>Iouinian,</hi> which you cite at randome without any number, I find nothing but this that may any way pleaſe you: <hi>In the type of his Blood he offered not Water, but Wine, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. This teſtimony I find alleaged by your Doctours as S. <hi>Hieroms,</hi> for their meere figuratiue or typicall Preſence; wherin they diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer eyther ignorance or deſire to deceaue their Readers. For whoſoeuer ſhall take the paynes to peruſe the place, will find the aforeſayd words not to be S <hi>Hieroms</hi> but <hi>Ioui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> whoſe diſcourſe againſt Abſtinence from fleſh and wine, S. <hi>Hierome</hi> there ſetts downe in that Heretike his owne wordes, whereof theſe are a part, <hi>In the Type of his Bloud he offered not water but wine.</hi> And S. <hi>Hierome</hi> afterward co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to anſwere this obeiction againſt drinking of water, and Abſtinence from Fleſh ſayth, that Chriſt neuer vſed wine nor dainties, <hi>excepto mysterio quo Typum ſuae paſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:21663:29"/>
expreſsit, &amp; pro probanda corporis veritate.</hi> Where the Saynt tearmes the holy Euchariſt a Type, not of the Body and Blood of Chriſt, as the Hereticke did; but of his Paſſion, which is repreſented in the Myſtery of the Maſſe, which is the ordinary Catholike Doctrine and phraſe.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding, ſeeing this Heretike, erred not agaynſt the Catholike Doctrine of the Reall Preſence, his wordes haue a true ſenſe, and make agaynſt you Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants. For you deny, that in his laſt Supper, he offered any thing at all, and ſay, that only vpon the Croſſe, he offered himſelfe once for all, not only ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently by his Bloud and Paſſion, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. but alſo effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually, agaynſt <hi>Mal.</hi> 2. without any other <hi>cleane oblation,</hi> for the application of the merit of his Paſſion vnto vs. This place therefore maketh not for you, neyther is it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny way againſt them though it were <hi>S. Hieroms,</hi> for they graunt he offered Wine in type or figure of his Bloud, but he offered alſo his Bloud, anſwering the figure in Truth and Subſtance. As he was Prieſt after the order of Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedech, in Bread and Wine, he offered Bread and Wine in figure: As the offering of Melchiſedech was a figure of his offering, he offered alſo his Body and Bloud, which was the Truth or Subſtance of that figure. Which to be the meaning of <hi>S. Hierome,</hi> may ſufficiently appeare by that which hath beene ſayd, and theſe other wordes of his <hi>Epist. ad Marcellam,</hi> doe make it yet to appeare more plainely ſaying: <hi>Melchiſedech in the Type of Christ offered Bread and Wine, and dedicated the Myſtery of Christians, in the Body and Bloud of our Sauiour.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:21663:30"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Section XII.</hi> Tertullian and Gelaſius falſly alleaged by Syr Humphry, agaynst the Reall Preſence. And S. Ignatius abſurdly claymed by the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Doctours.</head>
               <p>THere remayneth behinde of the Authors you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leage, <hi>Tertullian</hi> and <hi>Gelaſius.</hi> Tertullian is cleare for them, who in his Booke <hi>De reſurrectione car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis,</hi> to proue that our fleſh ſhall ryſe agayne and be ſaued, vſeth theſe words that follow: <hi>The flesh is washed, that the Soule may be clenſed. The flesh is annointed, that the Souls may be conſecrated. The flesh is fed with the Body and Bloud of Chriſt, that the Soule may be fatned.</hi> Though the Soule may feed on Chriſt by the metaphoricall mouth of Fayth; yet the fleſh hath no ſuch mouth to feede vpon him, and if it had, being only fed metaphorically therewith, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing would follow thereof, but that it might riſe and be ſaued only metaphorically; and ſo Tertullian ſhould haue proued that which he there impugned. In fine, as the fleſh is heere ſayd to be truly waſhed and annointed, ſo alſo it muſt be vnderſtood to be truly fed, and not to be fed by fayth only, or in figure.</p>
               <p>Which Argument to proue the Reſurrection, <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> ſeemeth to haue learned of <hi>Irenaeus lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cont. Haer. cap.</hi> 34. whome alſo he calleth <hi>Omnium Doctrinarum cario<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m Exploratorem. lib. cont. Valent. prope initium.</hi> And therfore becauſe the Doctrine of <hi>Irenaeus</hi> in that place doth ſerue very well to confirme both the doctrine of Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian, and the Reall Preſence heere in queſtion, I will giue you his whole diſcourſe. <hi>Quomodo constabit ijs &amp;c.</hi> (ſayth he of the Heretiks againſt whome he wrote) <hi>How
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:21663:30"/>
can they aſſure themſelues, the Bread wherein thankes are giuen, to be the body of their Lord, and</hi> (the Cup to be) <hi>the Cup of his bloud; if they do not confeſſe him, to be the Sonne of him that made the world? And how againe doe they ſay that, that flesh muſt go in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to corruption, and not receaue life, which is nourished by the body and bloud of our Lord? Therefore eyther let them change their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, or let them ceaſe to offer the things aforeſayd. But our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine agreeth with the Euchariſt, and the Eucharist againe confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth our Doctrine; for we offer</hi> (therin) <hi>vnto him thoſe things that are his,</hi> (becauſe being the Sonne of God, he maketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by his omnipotency his owne Body &amp; his owne Bloud) <hi>and conſequently we teach the communication and vnity of</hi> (his) <hi>Flesh, and of</hi> (his) <hi>Spirit</hi> (with vs; (our fleſh being fed with his Body and Bloud, and receauing thereby his Spirit to liue for euer.) <hi>For as the bread which commeth from the Earth, receauing the vocation</hi> (or word) <hi>of God, is now no more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon bread, but the Euchariſt, conſisting of two things, the one earthly</hi> (comming from the earth) <hi>and the other Heauenly,</hi> (the Body and Bloud of the Sonne of God:) <hi>ſo alſo our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies receauing the Eucharist</hi> (by the communication and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of his fleſh with ours) <hi>are no more corruptible, hauing now the hope of Reſurrection.</hi> So that according to theſe aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers; as we belieue our Sauiour to be the Sonne of God: ſo muſt we belieue the <hi>Eucharist</hi> to be his Body and Bloud. And as we belieue the Reſurrection of the Fleſh: ſo muſt we belieue that our fleſh is fed with the fleſh of Chriſt. And eyther you muſt change your opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, or els, as now you haue ceaſed to offer theſe things, and to feed your fleſh with the body and bloud of Chriſt; ſo you are alſo in danger to change your beliefe as well of the Diuinity of Chriſt, as alſo of the Reſurrection of your owne bodyes.</p>
               <p>But it may be, the place which your ſelfe haue ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cont. Marcionem,</hi> out of the ſame Author, is no leſſe with you the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was the former agaynſt you: his words are theſe: <hi>Profeſsing therefore that with a deſire he deſired to eate
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:21663:31"/>
the Paſche as his own</hi> (for it was not ſeemly that God ſhould deſire to eate the Paſche of another) <hi>hauing taken the Bread, &amp;c. he made it his owne body, ſaying: This is my body; that is, the figure of my body. But the figure had not beene, vnleſſe there were a true body.</hi> Whereof citing imperfectly, but halfe the Sentence: <hi>This is my body, This is the figure of my body,</hi> and changing <hi>that,</hi> into <hi>this,</hi> to make it ſound more fully for you, you guilefully omit the other halfe; <hi>The bread which he tooke he made his body, ſaying, This is my body:</hi> which are euidently againſt you. The words alſo which you cite, wherein the Author ſeemeth to ſay, <hi>This is my body; that is to ſay, this is the figure of my body,</hi> and no more, your Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries do clearly ſhew to haue another meaning.</p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe otherwiſe, he ſhould not only teach that which is directly contrary to his former Doctrine in the place before alleaged, but alſo ſhould contradict him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in this very ſentence: for according to our expoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhould not haue ſayd, that Chriſt tooke bread &amp; made it his body, which is falſe, if it be only a figure of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; but that he tooke bread, and made it the figure of his body, ſaying: This is my body, that is to ſay, the figure of my body, and conſequently in the words that follow, he ſhould haue ſayd, <hi>But it were not a figure vnleſſe there were a true body;</hi> and not as he doth, <hi>but there had not beene a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure,</hi> if there were not a true body. For if the figure and the body were both at the ſame tyme, why ſhould he ſay of the one, that it had beene, and of the other, that it was?</p>
               <p>Secondly, your Aduerſaries therefore do ſay, the meaning of thoſe words, <hi>This is my body,</hi> that is, <hi>the figure of my body,</hi> to be; <hi>This is my body,</hi> that is, <hi>the figure of my body in the law, now by me fullfilled;</hi> Or, <hi>This is my body,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>this is the bread which was a figure in the Law ſignifying my body, and is now fullfilled by me;</hi> hauing relatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the words of the Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi> which a little after he citeth and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth, and ſheweth to haue beene then fullfilled by
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:21663:31"/>
our Sauiour. As in the like ſenſe <hi>S. Iohn Baptist,</hi> for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, when he ſaw our Sauiour might haue ſayd, <hi>This is the Meſsias, that is to ſay, The Lambe of God which was the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of the Meſsias in the Law,</hi> to ſignify, that the Prophecy of the Lambe of God in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 16. was then fullfilled in our Sauiour.</p>
               <p>Therfore that Tertullian meant to ſay, <hi>This is my Body, that is to ſay, the figure of my Body,</hi> now fullfilled &amp;c. your Aduerſaries doe plainely proue. Firſt, becauſe it is euident that Tertullian in this place intended to ſhew how our Sauiour in his <hi>Paſche,</hi> fullfilled the law, againſt <hi>Marcion,</hi> who being an Enemy of the Old Teſtament, contended that our Sauiour came to diſſolue it; and Tertullian ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueth againſt him in this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner. The Bread of Chriſt in the law did ſignifie the Body of Chriſt, which he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth out of <hi>Ieremie</hi> 11. ſaying: <hi>Come, let vs put Wood on his Bread:</hi> that is (ſayth Tertullian) <hi>the Croſse vpon his Body.</hi> But our Sauiour gaue his Apoſtles, that Bread which he made his Body, ſaying, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> therefore he full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled the law, in giuing that Body which the law figured in Bread, and was therefore called Bread in <hi>Ieremie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the ſame manner againe he proueth, that giuing his Bloud in the forme of Wine, he fullfilled the law, becauſe he gaue that which the law figured in Wine, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Gen.</hi> 49. was called Wine, where it was propheſied of our Sauiour; <hi>That he should wash his ſtole in Wine, that is,</hi> (ſayth Tertullian) <hi>his Flesh in bloud;</hi> So ſayth Tertullian, he, <hi>qui tunc vinum in ſanguine figurauit,</hi> who then made Wine a figure of his Bloud, now conſecrated his Bloud in Wine.</p>
               <p>Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, your Aduerſaries proue the ſame, becauſe Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian vrgeth theſe former words, to proue alſo againſt <hi>Marcion,</hi> that our Sauiour had a true Body, and not the ſhadow or phantaſme only of a Body as he contended. Which ſuppoſing that his Body was (as Tertullian ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth) the figure of his Body then fullfilled; he proueth,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:21663:32"/>
becauſe vnto the figure of a Body to be <hi>Crucified,</hi> there muſt anſwere a true Body: <hi>for of a Phantaſme</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>there can be noe figure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly he proueth the ſame, <hi>Becauſe in the mention of the Cupp, inſtituting his Testament ſigned with his Bloud,</hi> he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed the ſubſtance of his Body. That is to ſay: he confirmed his Body to be no ſhadow, but a ſubſtance; for, ſayth he, <hi>the proof of Bloud, is a proof of Flesh; and the proof of Flesh, is a proofe of a true body.</hi> Wherefore hauing giuen Bloud in his Teſtament, he gaue alſo a true Body.</p>
               <p>Theſe Arguments therefore haue place, if according to the ſenſe which your Aduerſaries make of the words of Tertullian, <hi>Our Sauiour fullfilled the law, by giuing that which was figured in the law.</hi> But if according to your expoſition he gaue only a figure of his Body and Bloud; he gaue not that which was figured in the law, as Tertullian himſelf expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth the law; for that which was figured in the law (ſayth Tertullian) was that Body which was to be cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, &amp; by conſequence he fullfilled not the law: which notwithſtanding was the Hereſie of <hi>Marcion,</hi> there con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by Tertullian. And againe, if our Sauiour had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen that which was only a figure of his Body, Tertullian could not haue proued thereby, that our Sauiour had a true Body anſwerable to the figure therof, in the Prophet <hi>Ieremie.</hi> For if there might haue beene a figure of a figure, there might haue been alſo a figure of a Phantaſme. And if in the mention of the Cup, he had not ſigned his Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with true, but only with figuratiue Bloud, his Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament had not beene true, but only figuratiue; neyther had he thereby confirmed, that his Body was a true Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. For figuratiue Bloud, could haue proued but fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guratiue fleſh, and figuratiue fleſh could haue proued but a figuratiue Body.</p>
               <p>Add vnto this, that if in your ſenſe Tertullian hath ſayd, This is my Body, that is, the figure of my Body: <hi>Marcion</hi> might as well haue ſayd in lyke manner: This
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:21663:32"/>
is my Body, that is to ſay, the ſhadow, or Phantaſme of my Body. And ſo in effect, Tertullian had agreed with <hi>Marcion,</hi> whoſe Hereſy he there condemned; and had impugned the Truth of the <hi>Eucharist,</hi> which he there me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned; for as <hi>Ignatius</hi> long before obſerued the Simonian and the Saturnian Heretikes, <hi>did not admit Euchariſts and Oblations, becauſe they did not confeſſe the Euchariſt to be that flesh of our Sauiour which ſuffered for our ſinnes, Epist. ad Smyr. vt citatur à Theodoreto Dial.</hi> 3. Wherefore if <hi>Tertullian</hi> had not confeſſed the Euchariſt to be the fleſh of Chriſt, he muſt alſo haue denyed the Euchariſt and the oblatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof; and for the ſame reaſon the Proteſtants denying it to be the fleſh of Chriſt, and conſequently denying the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blation thereof, it is euident that they admitt not the Euchariſt of Ignatius, no more, then the Simonian and Saturnian Heretikes haue done before them; but inſteed of the Euchariſt which was in his dayes, they haue ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſititiouſly brought in another of their owne inuentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p>This is that S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> Martyr, the diſciple of S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> thought to be that Boy, who was found to haue the fiue Barly loaues and two fiſhes which our Sauiour mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplyed, that thereby the harts of men might be the better diſpoſed to belieue the locall multiplication of his owne body in the dreadfull Myſtery. Euen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence he tooke a great deuotion thereunto, and was euen then ordayned to be a witnes of the admirable Doctrine thereof. <hi>I delight not,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>Epist. ad Rom. post med. in the nutriment of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, I deſire the Bread of God, the Heauenly Bread, which is the Flesh of Chriſt the Sonne of God, and the drinke which is his Bloud,</hi> And as he had beene fed with the bread, which was Chriſts fleſh while he liued, ſo when he came to dye, he deſired that his fleſh might be grown'd as in a Mill with the teeth of Lyons, that he might be made cleane bread for the mouth of our Sauiour. Where alſo he ſayth: <hi>It is not lawfull without a Bishop</hi> (that is to ſay, without orders receaued from a Biſhop) <hi>to baptize, nor to immolate Sacrifice.</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:21663:33"/>
And what Proteſtant Miniſter will take vpon him, to immolate Sacrifice? Or what Proteſtant Biſhop, eyther can or will giue him power to doe it? For which cauſe the Centuriſts, <hi>Cent.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. affirme thoſe wordes of his, to be incommodious, <hi>Col.</hi> 55. dangerous, and as it were the ſeedes of errors, <hi>Col.</hi> 167. Yet this is that <hi>Ignatius</hi> of the firſt Age, whome your Doctors with vnſpeakable bould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes claymed to be theirs, as you know in the former Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference; and in their Booke would make fooles belieue, that the Catholikes when they heard him named, much reioyced, taking him to be <hi>Ignatius Loyola,</hi> the founder of the Society of IESVS. But the truth is, your Doctors might aſwell haue claymed the latter as the former. For i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his Religion be tryed by Workes, or Epiſtles that are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, then your Authors diſclayme from the former no leſſe then from the later. Your M. <hi>Wotton</hi> being vrged with the ſaying of <hi>Ignatius</hi> in the behalfe of Merit, taken out of his Epiſtle to the Romans, vndoubtedly his, as both <hi>S. Hierome</hi> and <hi>Euſebius</hi> acknowledge, yea <hi>S. Irenaeus (lib.</hi> 3. <hi>aduerſ. haereſ. prope finem</hi>) doth alleage a ſentence of this Epiſtle yet to be found therein: being I ſay, preſſed with this teſtimony, your Doctor in his defence of <hi>Perkins pag.</hi> 339. anſwereth in theſe wordes: <hi>I ſay plainely, this mans teſtimony is nothing worth, becauſe he was of little iudgment in Diuinity.</hi> What more could he haue ſayd in contempt of the teſtimony of S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> of <hi>Loyola?</hi> But your Grand Maiſter <hi>Caluin</hi> yet ſpeaketh more plainely in his Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 14. §. 44. <hi>Ignatium quòd obtendunt, nihil naenijs il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis quae ſub Ignatij nomine edita ſunt, putidius.</hi> Whereas they produce the teſtimony of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> I ſay nothing is more rotten or corrupted (with Papiſtry) then thoſe trifling Epiſtles that go vnder his name. If nothing be more rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, that is, more Papiſticall, and contrary vnto Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants then the Doctrine of the writings we haue of S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> the Apoſtles Diſciple, then is he aſmuch for vs as S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> of <hi>Loyolae.</hi> And the ſame M. <hi>Caluin</hi> in his
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:21663:33"/>
Booke <hi>de participatione Christi in Coena,</hi> whereas <hi>Westphalus</hi> the Lutheran alleadgeth the teſtimony of <hi>Ignatius</hi> cited by <hi>Theodoret</hi> in his 3. <hi>Dialogue,</hi> out of his Epiſtle <hi>ad Smir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enſes,</hi> where he chargeth the <hi>Menandrian</hi> Heretikes with his Caluinian hereticall Doctrine, <hi>Non confitentur Euchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stiam eſſe carnem Saluatoris noſtri Ieſu Chriſti,</hi> they do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue the Euchariſt to be the fleſh of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt; <hi>Caluin,</hi> I ſay, not without diſdayne frameth this anſwere: <hi>What ingenuity is this to cite the Epiſtle of Ignatius which euen an ordinary</hi> (Friar or) <hi>Monke would hardly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge as his owne? They know that haue read thoſe toyes that they contayne nothing but tales of Lent, of Chriſme, of Tapers, of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting, and feſtiuall dayes, which through ſuperſtition and ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce crept into the Church after Ignatius his dayes.</hi> Thus <hi>Caluin</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of the Epiſtle cited by <hi>Theodoret,</hi> by <hi>Euſebius,</hi> by S. <hi>Hierome,</hi> for the Epiſtle of <hi>Ignatius.</hi> So that as I ſayd, if the Religion of S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> the Diſciple of S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> be tryed by his writings, which all antiquity acknowledge as his, he is found, euen by the confeſſion of Proteſtants, as very a Papiſt as was <hi>S. Ignatius</hi> of <hi>Loyola,</hi> to wit, more then any ordinary Friar or Monke. What deſperation then was it of Doctour <hi>Featly,</hi> &amp; to what a <hi>Non-plus</hi> was he brought, when he was forced to giue vnto <hi>Ignatius</hi> and his wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings the firſt place after the Apoſtles in the Catalogue of Caluinian Profeſſors? For this Author can no more be coupled togeather with <hi>Caluin</hi> in the ſame Religion and Church, then light can agree with darknes, Chriſt with Beliall. Which (beſides what hath beene ſayd) may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in the Preface of his Epiſtle to the Romans, by the great <hi>Encomium</hi> he maketh of that Church, <hi>Quae praeſidet in Regione Romanorum;</hi> which preſidence muſt needs be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of the Church of Rome aboue other Churches.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, to draw to an end of this point, Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian ſeemeth to proue, that our Sauiour gaue his true bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, becauſe he profeſſed, <hi>That with a deſire he deſired to eate the Paſche as his owne; for that it had beene vnſeemely, that God
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:21663:34"/>
should haue longed after the flesh of the Iewish Lambe (or quid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienum) or after any thing els that was anothers.</hi> But if he had deſired to eate bread with his Apoſtles, he had not deſired to eate his owne, but that of another; and it had beene no leſſe vnſeemely, that God ſhould haue longed to eate the bread of another with his Apoſtles, then to eate fleſh of another with the Iewes.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, if this ſentence of Tertullian be obſcure, it muſt be expounded by the other place before alleadged, where he ſayth, without any ambiguity, that our fleſh is fed with the body and bloud of Chriſt. For it were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt all reaſon that the plaine words thereof ſhould be expounded by this other place, which ſeemeth to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne two contrary ſenſes, and therefore is often allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by vs agaynſt our Aduerſaries, and by our Aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries againſt vs.</p>
               <p>As concerning <hi>Gelaſius cont. Eutichem,</hi> the laſt Author that you alleage; I wil be content that <hi>Chemnitius</hi> a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Lutheran,</hi> and as great an Enemy of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> as your ſelfe, be iudge betweene vs, whether that place doth fauour it, or doth ſound any way for it: his words are theſe <hi>Examen. part.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 88. <hi>Gelaſius ſayth, that the Wine and the Bread of the Euchariſt, by the work of the holy Ghoſt, doe paſſe</hi> (or conuert) <hi>into the diuine Substance of the Body and Bloud of Christ; and verily theſe words do ſeeme to ſound very ſtrongly for the establishing of Tranſubſtantiation. For that which paſſeth into another ſubstance, and that by the working of the holy Ghoſt, certainely doth ſeeme, not to remaine in his former Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance.</hi> If you had ſeene this place, or if paſſion had not blinded you, had it beene poſſible you ſhould haue cited <hi>Gelaſius</hi> againſt <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> which by the iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of ſuch a profeſſed Enemy thereof, doth make ſo ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for it?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:21663:34"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Section XIII.</hi> The Concluſion of this Treatiſe.</head>
               <p>THus much concerning the Authories of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers alleaged by you, partly falſe cited, which may be pardoned; partly falſified, which ſeemeth to touch your Honour; and all of them eyther wholy peruerted, or far from the matter; which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming from a Knight ſheweth an excuſable ignorance in this kind of learning: But againſt the ſubſtance of the booke you receaued, as I haue ſhewed in the 4. firſt <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions</hi> of this Treatiſe, you haue anſwered nothing. Now therefore, good Syr, if according to your Degree, you will doe your owne ſelfe Knights ſeruice, indeed ſet to your ſhoulders, and vnderprop your Church, as <hi>Atlas</hi> was faigned to ſupport the heauens; for as you haue heard and ſeene in the former <hi>Sections,</hi> it is ſo mainely battered with fower ſuch peeces of great Ordinance, that vnleſſe it be mightly ſuſtained, the ſound of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alone is ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to ſhake it downe and ouerthow it. 1. Their viſible Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion in all Ages. 2. Their Conuerſions of Nations in all Ages. 3. Myracles in confirmation of their Doctrine in all Ages. 4. Cenſures of Fathers and Councells, for the condemnation of yours, in all Ages.</p>
               <p>For 1. your Doctors did but beg the Queſtion, when they made clayme to Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and began at the wrong end, making that their Argument, which ſhould haue beene their concluſion, &amp; was to be proued, by nominating Proteſtants to ſucceed them in all Ages, and eſpecially in the Ages before <hi>Luther,</hi> according to the words of the Queſtion, which they vndertooke, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere. What foule ſhame, and extreme confuſion is it to your Cauſe, when being vrged to name or bring forth but one Proteſtant in 500. or 1000. yeares, before <hi>Luther,</hi>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:21663:35"/>
you are eyther conſtrained to anſwere it is not neceſſary, or els ſuppoſing the ignorance of thoſe that heare you, yow are inforced to cloth your nakedneſſe, with the raggs of <hi>Wyckliffe</hi> &amp; <hi>Waldo,</hi> and other ſuch accurſed He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes; all of them holding ſome points with your Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries againſt you, and being for other groſſe hereſies noe leſſe deteſted by them, then condemned by you. Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let the bowells of <hi>Oxford Librarie</hi> be ripped vp, and ranſacked from end to end. Or els neuer leaue digging, vntill you haue wrought your ſelues into thoſe caues where Proteſtants liued for ſo many hundred yeares, to find ſome Volumes, ſome Comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taries, or ſome Records of the Actes and Geſtes of your Aunceſtors. If nothing can be found in Europe, recommend the matter to the Eaſt Indian Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany, or to the Weſterne <hi>Voyagers,</hi> to ſeeke and ſearch among furtheſt Nations, for Proteſtants, line<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally deſcended from Chriſt &amp; his Apoſtles; which being diſcouered, were better found then Mynes of gold. For vnleſſe by ſome ſuch meanes, the Profeſſors of your Ghoſpels may be brought to light, your Church cannot long continue aboue ground, but the former Queſtion alone, will ſuffice to coniure it downe againe into her auncient darkenes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. What can be more vnworthy, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Prieſts, Ieſuites,</hi> &amp; other <hi>Religious men</hi> execute the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our Sauiour in carrying his Ghoſpel to the ends of the Earth, as their Aunceſtors haue done in all Ages before them, thereby prouing themſelues their true Succeſſors, whome our B. Sauiour, according to his promiſe, <hi>Matt.</hi> 28. hath euer aſſiſted, and will alwaies acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany, <hi>Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and baptizing all Nations, Omnibus diebus, vſque ad conſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem ſaeculi,</hi> all dayes, or euery day vnto the end of the world: that your wiued Miniſters in the meane tyme, fatned with their benefices, ſhould only execute their owne malice in rayling vpon thoſe laborious men, and deprauing their Chriſtian endeauours, thereby ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:21663:35"/>
themſelues to be that peruerſe and baſtard generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which inſteed of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerting Infidells doth labour only to ſubuert belieuers; inſteed of planting the faith of Chriſt, only indeauor to extirpate that Faith, which they found to be already planted; &amp; inſteed of ſowing the firſt corne, only ſcatter cockle and darnell vpon that corne which was firſt ſowed by others. Rather ſet forth whole fleets of Miniſters, with their numerous families both for the Eaſt, and for the Weſt, to bring thoſe miſerable Nations vnto the liberty and light of the Ghoſpell, that haue layne ſo long captiue vnder the foule bondage and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable Tiranny of the Prince of darknes. Then it would be quikly tryed whether in thoſe parts the diuells would ſubmit themſelues, and fly before them: or, <hi>Whether like the ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger party Luc.</hi> 11.18. as hitherto in Virginia they haue ſhewed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, <hi>they would be able to keepe in peace the ſoules and veſſells which they haue there ſoe long poſſeſsed;</hi> vntill there come others ſtronger the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your Miniſters that may be able to bind them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. What can be more impious, then whereas your Aduerſaries, like true Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s confirme their doctrine in all Ages by thoſe ſignes &amp; myraculous operations, which were promiſed to follow the true belieuers, <hi>Marc.</hi> 16.17. you on the other ſide ſhould haue nothing to anſwere, but only like Iewes and Pagans to laugh at them, and at the holy Fathers themſelues that were ſo ſimple, as eyther to teſtify or to belieue them. Rather ioyne your harts and your hands togeather, that once in your tyme, you may ſee a Generall Councell from all Proteſtant Prouinces meete togeather, where out of ſo many Religions ſpru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vp amongſt you, hauing choſen one by Lot to be gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally profeſſed, beſeech him, who heareth all thoſe that with a true Fayth doe call vpon him, to confirme that choſen doctrine by ſome oſtenſion in the <hi>Sunne,</hi> or in the <hi>Moone,</hi> or with ſome ſuch notorious ſigne from Heauen, as might no leſſe exceed the former Myracles of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:21663:36"/>
then the wondrous workes of <hi>Moyſes,</hi> confounded the magicall practiſes of the Egiptian Sages.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And laſtly, what can be more voyde of ſhame and conſcience, then to clayme thoſe Fathers of the firſt 500. yeares for yours, that haue ſo impartially cenſured ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſeuerall points of your Doctrine in the Heretikes of their tymes (for the which I refer me to the fourth Sectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this Treatiſe) as he that conſidereth them, may iuſtly eſteeme the body of your Religion to be almoſt nothing els, but only a confarcination or bundle of old Hereſies, condemned by them. Rather ioyne all in prayer, that if your Cauſe be true, as Almighty God vouchſafed in his owne perſon, to iuſtify <hi>Iob,</hi> againſt his friends; ſo that our Sauiour would be pleaſed with a voyce from Heauen, to iuſtify you agaynſt the Fathers. But ouer Shooes, ouer Head and Eares, ſayth the Prouerbe; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding whereunto, if being once entred into a bad cauſe, it be reſolued, that ſtill you muſt needes goe forward; ceaſing to falſify the words, and to peruert the meaning of thoſe holy Fathers, leaſt God in his iuſtice double your puniſhment, as you double your iniquity, hold your ſelues to the Scripture alone, and to your owne interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Scripture (with M. <hi>Luther,</hi> and M. <hi>Caluin,</hi> and thoſe learned Proteſtants of your owne Nation for ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares togeather) not fearing to reiect the Fathers that were but men, and directly refuting their errors<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for in ſo doing, though you ſhould want verity, yet God might be pleaſed at the length, to haue mercy vpon you for your ſincerity.</p>
               <p>O Mercifull God, the Author of all truth! If you be in the truth, why ſhould you defend it by fraud and fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhood! And how can it ſtand with his good will and pleaſure, that againſt ſo many powerfull Arguments and euident demonſtrations to the contrary, you ſhould any longer thus contentiouſly hold it? And obſtinately ſo continue to profeſſe it?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:21663:36"/>Certainly thoſe 4. Conſiderations before remembred and reported more at large in the 4. firſt Sections of this Treatiſe, do make it ſo euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto me, that theirs &amp; not yours is the only true viſible &amp; vniuerſall Church orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and founded by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, to teach the world; that I wonder in my hart how any learned Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant can be ſo blinde as not to ſee it, or ſo voyd of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, as not to confeſſe it. Neyther if I were now a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant ſhould any thing with-hold me from ioyning my ſelfe vnto them, vnleſſe it were only in honor of that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion wherein I was bred, to expect a little, <hi>Whether the foreſayd Catalogue</hi> of the Names of your Profeſſors in all Ages, and eſpecially in the Ages before <hi>Luther,</hi> might be found and produced. The Queſtion is now very happily ſet on foot; I hope it wilbe ſoundly followed; and it were to be wiſhed, that no other Controuerſy might be imbraced, before this, which is but matter of fact and the key of all the reſt, be fully cleared. If Satisfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may be giuen in this poynt, you may the better hope to be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in the reſt. But if not ſo much as one man can be produced in 500. yeares before <hi>Luther,</hi> that held not ſome maine points of Popery againſt you, or ſome other groſſe errors condemned by you: if when <hi>Luther</hi> firſt began, not one Proteſtant can be named, that did not firſt fall from the Religion wherein he was bred, or which he had firſt receaued; then certainly it is not to be marueiled, if thouſands and thouſands ere it be long, doe renounce &amp; abandone (with prayer for thoſe to come after the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whom they ſhall leaue behind them) that vpſtart Fayth which was new when <hi>Luther</hi> began, and none at all before <hi>Luther.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>ALmighty God, inſpire the hart of his Majeſty, whom it importeth noe leſſe then our ſelues, that whereas the Catholike Recuſants were neuer as yet accuſed of hereſy, according to forme of Eccleſiaſticall iuſtice, much leſſe ſommoned and called to make their anſwere, or iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridically
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:21663:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned; &amp; that their Enemies formerly ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by Generall Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cells according to the Auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Law and receaued cuſtome of the Church, haue notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, beene hitherto admitted, not only as accuſers, but alſo as witneſſes and iudges againſt them, whereby the people of the Land, being conſtrained to heare the one party, and reſtrained from hearing the other, haue been morally compelled to loue the one and hate the other, to magnify the one and deteſt the other; his Maieſty would be pleaſed to gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto all his louing ſubiects, for the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of their poore Soules committed to his charge, that now at the le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth they might be allowed both their eares, to heare both ſides indifferently, to weigh and ponder both cauſes, and well to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider of both Religions. Left vnder the plauſible name of ſpirituall liberty, they be cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly held in miſerable captiuity: being flattered with the ſhew of light, they be inſnared in dubble darkenes: &amp; being deluded with preſumption of knowlege, they be bound and buried in moſt dredfull ignorance. A requeſt ſoe fauorable both in the ſight of God and Man, and ſo agreable to the principles of Proteſtant Religion, as I thinke it can be vngratefull to none, who doe wiſh vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fainedly, that only falſhood may be ſuppreſſed, and the truth maintained. For the which all thoſe that ſincerely deſire to ſerue God vprightly, ſhallbe infinitely obliged to pray for his Maieſty; not only as for their Gratious King, but alſo as for their deliuerer from the thraldome of conſcience wherein he found them, and for the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of their chiefeſt liberty wherin he ſhould place the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21663:37"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
